<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Karolou trismegistou epiphania the most glorious star, or celestial constellation of the Pleiades, or Charles Waine, appearing, and shining most brightly in a miraculous manner in the face of the sun at noonday at the nativity of our sacred soveraign King Charles 2d, presaging His Majesties exaltation to future honour and greatness transcending not only the most potent Christian princes in Europe but by divine designment ordained to be the most mighty monarch in the universe : never any star having appeared before at the birth of any (the highest humane hero) except our Saviour / by Edw. Matthew ...</title>
            <author>Matthew, Edward.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 156 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 88 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50289</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1309</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R19177</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12561100</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12561100</idno>
            <idno type="VID">63183</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50289)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 63183)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 768:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Karolou trismegistou epiphania the most glorious star, or celestial constellation of the Pleiades, or Charles Waine, appearing, and shining most brightly in a miraculous manner in the face of the sun at noonday at the nativity of our sacred soveraign King Charles 2d, presaging His Majesties exaltation to future honour and greatness transcending not only the most potent Christian princes in Europe but by divine designment ordained to be the most mighty monarch in the universe : never any star having appeared before at the birth of any (the highest humane hero) except our Saviour / by Edw. Matthew ...</title>
                  <author>Matthew, Edward.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 156 p., 2 leaves of plates : port.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for J. Stafford and Edw. Thomas ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title transcribed from Greek.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  II, --  King of England, 1630-1685.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles II, 1660-1685.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:63183:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A Repreſentation of his late Majesty King Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> first His giving Thankes to Almighty God for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> birth of his Sonne (now our most Gratious Soveraigne) King Charles y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. at S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Pauls London May the 29<hi rend="sup">th</hi>: 163<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi>
                  </p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:63183:1"/>
            <p>ΚΛΠΟ'ΛΟΥ <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>THE MOST GLORIOUS STAR, OR, CELESTIAL CONSTELLATION OF THE <hi>Pleiades,</hi> or <hi>Charles</hi> Waine, Appearing, And ſhining moſt brightly in a <hi>Miraculous</hi> manner in the Face of the Sun at Noon day at the <hi>Nativity</hi> of our Sacred Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign <hi>KING Charles</hi> 2d. Preſaging his Majeſties <hi>Exaltation</hi> to future Honour and Greatneſs Tranſcending not only the moſt potent Chriſtian Princes in <hi>Europe,</hi> but by Divine deſignment ordained to be the moſt <hi>Mighty Monarch</hi> in the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe:</hi> Never any Star having appeared before at the birth of any (the <hi>Higheſt humane Hero</hi>) except our Saviour.</p>
            <q>Behold, a <hi>King</hi> ſhall reign in righteouſneſs — <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal. 32.1.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>By <hi>Edw. Matthew</hi> of the Middle <hi>Temple,</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>J. Stafford</hi> and <hi>Edw. Thomas,</hi> and are to be ſold neer the <hi>White-hart</hi> in <hi>Smithfield,</hi> and at the <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> in <hi>Little-Britain.</hi> 1660.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:63183:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:63183:2"/>
            <head>To the moſt Auguſtuous Prince my Dear and Dread So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign <hi>Charlemain</hi> the 2d. by the Mercy and Divine decree of the Almighty, his Highneſs own Inhaerent Inheritance, and legal Succeſſion, The peoples ſurpaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing deſire, ſignal Loyalty, long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing affection, and eſpecial Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, of Great <hi>Britain, France,</hi> and <hi>Ireland, Jure Divino &amp; humano,</hi> King Defender of the true anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Chriſtian Catholick Faith, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And by Divine Providence preordained to be the moſt pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, prudent and potent Prince in the Univerſe.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Ructavit Cor me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um verbum bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num; Dico ego opera mea Regi, Pſal. 45.1.</hi> My heart is Indit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a good matter, concerning
<pb facs="tcp:63183:3"/>the <hi>King;</hi> Divine providence diſpoſing my Meditations to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards ſo ſacred a ſubject, directs the Dedication thereof according to the Princely Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Davids</hi> pattern. <hi>Dico o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pera mea Regi. Quod auſus ſum tantae Majeſtatis Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pem tantillo adire munuſculo</hi> That ſo mean a perſon ſhould approach the preſence of ſo mighty a Prince, with ſo poor a preſent may be accounted high preſumption; yet 'tis ſtoried, that <hi>Jupiter</hi> was pleaſed with the courſe fare of a poor perſon.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Baucis in hoſpitium magnum acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſſe Tonantem,</l>
               <l>Atque illi inſuaves appoſuiſſe dapes, &amp;c.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder the law he that had not a Lamb to ſacrifice, was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
<pb facs="tcp:63183:3"/>to offer a <hi>Turtle Dove,</hi> or pair of young <hi>Pigeons,</hi> and in the Goſpel a ſmall Mite ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders a poor Widdow Liberall, <hi>Aeſchines</hi> when he ſaw his fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Schollers preſenting great gifts to <hi>Socrates</hi> their Maſter, being deſtitute of ſuch a preſent, preſented himſelf, profeſſing <hi>to be wholy devoted to his Maſter, which Socrates ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted as the chiefeſt Gift.</hi> There is nothing worth your <hi>Majeſties</hi> acceptance in the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of Your Highneſſe meaneſt ſubject, Paraſitical adulation I know unpleaſing to your pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent <hi>Majeſty,</hi> and hateful to mine own Nature, my Life and what elſe can be accounted dear
<pb facs="tcp:63183:4"/>
               <hi>uſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ad aras,</hi> I have bin alwaies and ſtill ſhall be moſt freely ready to ſacrifice. 'Tis ſaid of <hi>Caeſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r</hi> that ſurely nature meant him for a Conqueror, when ſhe gave him both ſuch courage and ſuch courteſie which put <hi>Marius</hi> into a muze (ſaying) that he that du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt ſpeak to him, was ignorant of his greatneſſe, and he that durſt not was ſo of his goodneſſe.</p>
            <p>The incomparable Candor of your <hi>Majeſties</hi> ſweeteſt diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion gives me incouragement humbly to implore Your <hi>Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties</hi> princely pardon for this preſumption, and to vouchſafe your Highneſſe Gracious accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of this unpoliſhed piece,
<pb facs="tcp:63183:4"/>penner whilſt my Soule (though inlarged with ſurpaſſing Love and Joy for my Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigns ſafe and happy Reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, (for which my prayers to Heaven were frequent and conſtant, my Tounge and Pen Head, Heart, and Hands ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to my beſt ability not wanting) yet was much ſtreight<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned with perplexity of ſpirit, by reaſon of long impriſonment and diſtracted with diſtemper of Mind and Eſtate alwaies at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending the ſad Condition of Priſoners! Happily herein ſomewhat not unworthy your <hi>Majeſties</hi> ſerious conſideration at preſent) may be obſerved: &amp; I hope I have herein delivered
<pb facs="tcp:63183:5"/>nothing touching your <hi>Majeſty</hi> but what I have received from the dictates of that Good Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine ſpirit which hath directed me through this whole diſcourſe and what I faithfully believe will in due time be fully ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed, my faith herein be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in part confirmed not only by thoſe propheticall preſages in this Tract ſpecified, and by Dreams &amp; Viſions (which how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever by ſome may be accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vain or deceitful) yet I have often proved, &amp; ſince found re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to come to paſs, and receive a plenary effect touching your <hi>Majeſties</hi> return and other matters of Moment: But alſo by an irreſiſtible and invincible preſſure of ſpirit, to publiſh
<pb facs="tcp:63183:5"/>what in this tract, I have writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten; ſo that I may truly ſay with the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah, 'Twas a fire in my bones, and I could not ſupreſſe it,</hi> but by Divine impulſion of ſpirit, was importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and preſt to declare what by divine deſignment I believe is determined touching your <hi>Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties</hi> exaltation not only to be the moſt potent Chriſtian Prince in <hi>Europe,</hi> But to be the phenix of this Age, and the moſt Famous and Illuſtrious potentate in the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe. This I ſhall be ready to avouch againſt the moſt criti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call carpers murmuring and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracting Momuſſes, and ſeeming zealous Zoyluſſes; and 'tis pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable ſome pernicious <hi>Paſhurs</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:63183:6"/>wil conſpire with other confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates <hi>cogitare cogitationes</hi> to deviſe deviſes againſt <hi>Jeremiah</hi> and be ready <hi>percutere eum lingua,</hi> to ſmite him with the tongue, <hi>Jer. 18.18.</hi> Their malice ſhall render them nothing more then <hi>Paſhurs</hi> reward, but a new name of terror and ſhame, <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gor miſſabib</hi> ſignifying fear round about, we have of late unhappily had too many <hi>paſhurs</hi> who cannot abide to hear any truth ſpoken, ſuch as wil not hear any good declared or proſperity preſaged to their Prince, how pious &amp; worthy ſoever, but are ready rather to calumniate; let all ſuch ſeditions <hi>Shebaes,</hi> Curſing <hi>Shimei's,</hi> Railing <hi>Rabſhekeis,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:63183:6"/>&amp; rebellious <hi>Korahs</hi> know, that though they rail &amp; rage, againſt their lawful Soveraign againſt whom they ought not to entertain ſo much as an evil thought, he that ſits in Heaven will not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deride but in the end deſtroy all ſuch diſturbing Traytors, &amp; will eſtabliſh your Majeſties Throne in righteouſneſs, cauſe your Highneſſe Crown to flouriſh and cloth your Enemies with ſhame &amp; confuſion in concluſion. The King of Kings hath ſet his King on high upon his holy Hill, his Sion, over his People; &amp; ſent an heavenly Herald to proclaim his preſent power, and declare a future inlargement of his Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion; A glorious Star, or rather<gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:63183:7"/>flial Conſtellation, the <hi>Pleiades Charles Waine,</hi> ſhining bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie on the day of your Majeſties Nativity, when your Majeſties late pious Father of bleſsed me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory came to offer his ſacriſice of praiſe as Incenſe at the Alter of St. <hi>Paul.</hi> That Celeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Embaſſadour was ſent to certifie Gods acceptance of that ſacrifice, and to confirm the certainty of your Majeſties fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Exaltation, to tranſcendent honour by divine deſignment preordained. <hi>E Caelis tanti beneficii mittitur nunciusquia nemo in terras illius magnitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinem nec intelligebat, nec credebat</hi> (as was ſaid of our Saviours ſtar appearing upon
<pb facs="tcp:63183:7"/>his Nativity) <hi>Caeleſtium mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerum merito caeleſtis nunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us eſt,</hi> the people neither under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding nor believing the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and goodneſſe of the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit beſtowed on them, an heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly nuntio is therefore ſent to aſsure them of both. I have wuch more to ſpeak concerning Your ſacred Majeſty who may well be reſembled to the Golden Gandleſtick, and the two Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned Dukes, your Majeſties Royal Brethren to the two Olive Trees on the right and left ſide thereof <hi>Zech. 4.</hi> But leaſt I ſhould incurre the cenſure of the City of <hi>Myndas</hi> for making my Porch to large, I ſhall crave your Majeſties pardon, and Conclude
<pb facs="tcp:63183:8"/>with the prayer of that Princely Prophet your Majeſties moſt pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Father, I pray God bleſse Your Majeſty and eſtabliſh Your Kingdoms in righteouſneſs, your ſoul in true Religion, and your honour in the love of God and your People, which is and ſhall be the dayly and hearty prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Moſt Gracious SOVERAIGN.</salute>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Though one of the Loweſt, yet no leſs Loyall and Faithfull then the Loftieſt of your Majeſties Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects and Servants,</hi>
                  <hi>Edw. Matthew.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:63183:8"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:63183:9"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The high and Mighty Monarch Charles the ſecond by the grace of god King of England. Scotland, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> France, and Ireland defender of the faith</hi>
                  </p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:63183:9"/>
            <head>ΚΛΠΟ'ΔΟΥ <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Sidus ſive Currus Triumphalis Careli à Carolo, majoris Carolo magno.</hi>
            </head>
            <head>The glorious Star of King <hi>Charls</hi> II. <hi>Or, the Triumphall Charriot of the Brittiſh Charlemaine, Charles-waine.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lmighty God the King of Kings, to whom the Shield and Pillars of the Earth belong, by whom Kingsraign, Princes bear rule, and Rulers have Dominion, as he is the Authour, Giver and Diſpoſer of Dignities, Honours and higheſt promotions; So his Divine Majeſty is oftentimes pleaſed by remarkable preceding ſignes, to demonſtrate his purpoſe of doing great things, for thoſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, whom his Omniſcient Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome predeſtinateth to ſuperlative
<pb n="1" facs="tcp:63183:10"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:63183:11"/>Honour and Greatneſſe. To omit Heathen Hiſtory, holy Writ is full and frequent in Examples of this nature, ſignes coeleſtiall, by Angels, Stars, ſignes in the Heavens, Light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, Thunders, Clouds, and very frequently by fires from heaven, or bright-ſhining lights, and flames and pillars of fires alſo on Earth; alwayes evident infallible preſages, to perſons or places, publique or private of extraordinary mercies or Judgements enſuing.</p>
            <p>To inſtance in ſome few (for to mention all would be too tedious) the Lord by Angels and Viſions of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten appeared to <hi>Abraham,</hi> touching his ſeed and eſtate; ſo to <hi>Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob;</hi> And upon <hi>Moſes</hi> his call to be Leader of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> out of Aegypt, the houſe of Bondage; the Angel of the Lord appeared to him in a flame of fire, in <hi>a buſh burning,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:63183:11"/>but not conſumed;</hi> Exod. 3.2. Gods mercy herein is evidenced to <hi>Moſes</hi> and his people; And after Gods Judgments againſt their Enemies, who kept them in bondage, is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted by many miracles, ſhewed by the power of God in the hand of <hi>Moſes, Exod:</hi> 9.23. who (<hi>inter alia</hi>) ſtretching out his rod towards hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, The Lord ſendeth haile, min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled with fire, thunder and light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning on man and beaſt.</p>
            <p>The Iſraelites marching out of Aegypt, the Lord goeth before them, by day in a Pillar of a Cloud, and by night in a Pillar of Fire, <hi>Exod.</hi> 13.21.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aaron</hi> ſpeaking to the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of Iſrael, <hi>the glory of the Lord appeareth</hi> in a <hi>cloud</hi> towards the Wilderneſſe, <hi>Exod.</hi> 16.10.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Moſes</hi> coming down from mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> with the two Tables in his hand, his Face ſhineth ſo
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:63183:12"/>bright, that <hi>Aaron</hi> and the people are afraid to come neer him, <hi>Exod.</hi> 34.30.</p>
            <p>On the third day before giving of the law, thunder, lightning, thick Clouds, and the mount <hi>Sinai</hi> trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling, <hi>&amp;c. Exod.</hi> 19.16.</p>
            <p>An Angel of the Lord appeared to <hi>Manoah</hi> and his wife, predicting the Conception and Birth of <hi>Sam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pſon,</hi> and they offering Sacrifice, the Angel aſcended in the flame which came from the Altar, <hi>Judges</hi> 13. A wonderfull ſigne preſaging <hi>Sam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pſons</hi> ſurpaſſing ſtrength, to be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of God; and therefore tis ſaid when he ſhewed any Acts of his va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour and force, <hi>The ſpirit of the Lord came mightily upon him, Jud.</hi> 14.6.15.14.</p>
            <p>The Angel <hi>Gabriel</hi> was ſent of God, to declare to the bleſſed Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin <hi>Mary</hi> her Conception and birth of our Saviour, and give him the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:63183:12"/>name <hi>Jeſus,</hi> and prenunciate his goodneſs and greatneſs, <hi>Mat.</hi> 1.21. <hi>Luke</hi> 1, 31.32. A Saviour of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and he ſhall be great, and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the ſon of the moſt high, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After his birth, there appeared a Star, by which the <hi>Magi,</hi> the great wealthy and wiſemen of the Eaſt were directed to Chriſt, who came and worſhipped, and preſented rich gifts, Gold, Frankincenſe, and Myrrhe, <hi>&amp;c. Mat.</hi> 2.11.</p>
            <p>On the Birth-day of our Soveraign Lord the King, being Saturday 29. of <hi>May,</hi> 1630. a bright ſtar at noon ſhone gloriouſly in the heavens, his late Majeſty coming then to hear a Sermon at St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Croſſe; the Text whereof was, <hi>Sampſons Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleme or riddle, Jud.</hi> 14, 14. <hi>Out of the strong came forth ſweetneſſe, &amp;c.</hi> And to preſent his praiſe &amp; peace-Offering at St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Altar, for the Royall Queens happy delivery of our then hopefull Prince: our now
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:63183:13"/>moſt bleſſed, loved and honoured, King, <hi>Charlemaine,</hi> the II. from a plain but happily prophetical Pen; this threefold diſtichon then dropped.</p>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Rex Pauliu as accelſit gratus ad aras,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Emicnit medio ſplendida stella die.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Dic Diuina mihi tractans Aenign<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ata praeco,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> prudicat ſtella <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ntanda micans.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> in Occiduo princeps jam naſcitur orbe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Luct un &amp; ecclipſi cras Orientis erit.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Thus Engliſhed.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>Whileſt to the Altar of St. <hi>Paul</hi> the King</l>
                  <l>Approached with his grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Offering:</l>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:63183:13"/>
                  <l>A Star at noon appeared; tell me divine?</l>
                  <l>That preacheſt Riddles, why it then did ſhine?</l>
                  <l>To the Weſtern world a Prince is newly born;</l>
                  <l>And the Eaſt too morrow in Ecclipſe ſhall mourn.</l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>That there was on the day fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing being Sunday, an Orientall Ecclipſe cannot be doubted; The effects and operation of which are yet in future to be produced, of which ſomething ſhall be ſaid here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</p>
            <p>At the death of <hi>Julius Caeſar, Qui in Deorum numerum relatus eſt,</hi> who was numbred among the Gods, a Comet ſhined then for ſeven dayes together, ariſing about the eleventh houre of the day, which by the blinde Heathens was believed to be <hi>Caeſars</hi> ſoul, who had been a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met of Combuſtion to the World,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:63183:14"/>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Horace lib. <hi>1.</hi> ode <hi>12.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <l>— micat inter omnes</l>
                  <l>Julium ſidus, velut inter ignes</l>
                  <l>Luna minores.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>But what Hiſtory do we finde mentioning the Apparition of any celeſtial ſigne or ſtar, at the Birth of any the greateſt perſons before or ſince our Saviour? Surely, none of our higheſt humane <hi>Hero</hi>'s have been honoured herewith; but our Sacred Soveraign, upon whoſe Nativity in the mid-day, in the face of the Sun this Star appeared, and ſhined moſt brightly, in the fight of many of good credit, yet living to teſtifie the Truth hereof.</p>
            <p>Let none maliciouſly miſtake me, as though I compared our King with the worlds Saviour, far be it from even my imaginations, much more expreſſions; I know his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty as much abominates pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane adoration, as he hates para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitical Adulation: I ſhall therefore
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:63183:14"/>onely ſet down ſome brief but ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous obſervations of reſemblance happening touching that Star, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing at the Nativity of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, and this Star or ſigne C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtiall ſhining at the Nativity of our Soveraign, and leave the ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, interpretation and ampli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication thereof to ſome diviner Pens.</p>
            <p>The firſt Obſervation, is, that as that Star did lead the wiſemen to Chriſt to worſhip his divine Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, ſo the wiſer and better ſort of men were directed by divine Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence to yield due honour and obedience to our rightfull Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Lord and King, which by wilfully wicked perſons was long withdrawn and denyed.</p>
            <p>The ſecond, That as Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus was the worlds coeleſtiall and eternal Saviour, ſent into the world
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:63183:15"/>to ſave his people from their ſins, and Death &amp; Hell due for the ſame, and therefore had the ſweet name Jeſus given him by the Angel from God: So hath God ſent our Soveraign King to be a Terreſtial, temporal Savior to our Microcroſm; theſe three Nations, ready to ſinck in miſery &amp; ſlavery, and to be ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed up by divelliſhly minded Miſcreants, Rebellious Traitors, walking craftily, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Such as <hi>Jere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiah</hi> the Prophet mentions, <hi>chap.</hi> 6.28.</p>
            <p>But God hath made our King as tis ſaid, <hi>v.</hi> 27. of that Chapter; I have ſet thee for a Tower and a Fortreſſe among my people, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And <hi>chap.</hi> 15.20. <hi>I will make thee unto this people, a fenced brazen wall, though they fight against thee, they ſhall not prevaile; for I am with thee to ſave thee, and to deliver thee, ſaith the Lords.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, as the wiſemen of the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:63183:15"/>Eaſt ſeeing the Star, came to Chriſt, and rejoyced with great joy, and fell down and worſhipped him, and opened their Treaſures, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to him Gold, Incenſe and Myrrhe, <hi>Mat.</hi> 2.10, 11. So hath the Lord touched and wonderfully inclined the hearts of the people towards our gracious King, that with inexpreſſible joy, and ſurpaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing affection, they bow and ſubmit to his Majeſty, with rich Preſents, in token of Love, Loyalty and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage: As the prophetical King, and Kingly Prophet <hi>David,</hi> of our Saviour propheſied; <hi>The Daughter of</hi> Tyre <hi>ſhall be there with a gift, like as the rich alſo among the people ſhall doe hommage before thy face, with pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents.</hi> Pſal. 45.12. Is not this Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture fulfilled at this time in our ſight? Again, Pſal. 68.29. <hi>Kings ſhall bring preſents unto thee, the Kings of</hi> Arabia <hi>and</hi> Saba <hi>ſhall bring gifts, &amp;c.</hi> This is in part fulfilled
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:63183:16"/>by the King of <hi>Spaines</hi> Royall and kinde Prefents, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But will here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after be more fully accompliſhed, but by whom and in what manner, the ſame ſhall be done (although I have good ground for my Faith herein) I ſhall at preſent conceale, another opportunity happily for diſcovery hereof may be fitter.</p>
            <p>Many propheticall expreſſions in holy Writ might be produced; properly appliable to our Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign, King <hi>Charls,</hi> and even parallel to the preſent times and occaſions, a ſhort Tract whereof hath been penned a year ſince, but not yet publiſhed; which I now forbear to ſpecifie, intending onely at preſent to ſpeak and write of the ſaid Stars Apparition at his Majeſties Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity, and obſervations thereupon.</p>
            <p>Yet thus much, I crave leave to ſay (I truſt without offence to God or good men) and propoſe this <hi>quare;</hi> What man, ever more like
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:63183:16"/>the Son of man our Saviour, in his humanity, then this our Sacred King in ſeveral reſpects, as he was:</p>
            <p n="1">1. (In his own perſon) born to be a King: 2 Pointed at by an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Star: 3. Both in his pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Fathers perſon perſecuted, and in his own purſued into exile, both in a worſe caſe then Birds &amp; Foxes, who have neſts and holes: Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities upon calamities accumula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted upon Innocent heads, (our late Soveraigne at length, cauſeleſly yet barbaroufly murthered at his own gate.) 4. Slandered as a Friend of Papiſts and Malignants, as our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour Chriſt of publicans and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners; and many other ſuch like ſufferings as our Saviours. Yet <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rietur ſtella ex Jacob &amp; conſurget virga de Iſrael &amp; percuties duces Moab, vaſtabitque, &amp;c.</hi> Number 24.17, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There ſhall come a Star out of peaceable <hi>James</hi> the Olive-bearer of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:63183:17"/>this Iſle, and a Scepter ſhall riſe out of pious <hi>Charls</hi> (a precious Martyr for the Laws of the Land, and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties of the People.) <hi>Ex Jacob erit qui dominetur,</hi> Num. 24.19. <hi>de forti egreſſa eſt dulcedo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Out of the ſtrong ſhall come the ſweet, a Ruler ſo pleaſing, ſo much longed for, &amp; deſired by the People.</p>
            <p>What King except our coeleſtial Soveraign and King <hi>David,</hi> ever rod on ſo many Clouds of Calamities? ever bare ſuch a burthen of bitter miſeries? yet (maugre the malice of al the moſt potent oppoſers.) Me thinks I hear the Lord thus comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his King &amp; people; I will raiſe up for them a glorious plant of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nown; And they ſhall be no more conſumed, nor bear the ſhame of the enemy for Rebellion any more; I will raiſe up a righteous Branch, A King ſhall raign and proſper. <hi>Jer.</hi> 23. I will give the Crown and Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem to him, whoſe due and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:63183:17"/>right it is, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 21. Tis well worth our obſervation; ſeven ſeveral ſorts of Government in this laſt Years ſpace, ſought and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to be ſet up; yet <hi>Iniquita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem, iniquitatem, iniquitatem ponam eam,</hi> ſaith the Lord, perverted, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted, perverted will I make it; <hi>Yet have I ſet my King upon my holy, hill of</hi> Sion, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2. The Lord made <hi>David</hi> proſper in all his procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, what ever <hi>David</hi> did was pleaſing to the people; their ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der care of him was ſuch, that they ſaid, thou art more worth then ten thouſand of us: The King of of Kings owneth eminently and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidently our King, as he did King <hi>David,</hi> to be his King, on whom are ſet the hearts of all the people? Hath he not united and knit them faſt, unto his and their King? Is not our King (by Gods grace to his Majeſty) become the love and longing of his people, even the joy
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:63183:18"/>of their hearts? They have been (with the ſpouſe in the <hi>Canticles</hi>) ſick for love, for lack of his Majeſty, their dearly beloved Soveraign, and which is a ſignal Note of Gods love likewiſe; thoſe that were his very enemies are not onely now in peace, but in love with his Majeſty; And as <hi>Balaam</hi> for <hi>Balac,</hi> though hired to curſe, yet bleſſe altogether; The Lord God is with him, and the ſhout of a King is among them; Surely, there is no inchantment a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Jacob,</hi> nor divination againſt <hi>Iſrael:</hi> Our <hi>Charlemaine,</hi> accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to this time, it ſhall be ſaid, what God hath wrought, <hi>Numb.</hi> 23.21, 23. <hi>As the trees,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>which the Lord hath planted, and as the Cedar Trees be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the waters; The King ſhall be higher than</hi> Agag, <hi>and his Kingdome ſhall be exalted. Bleſſed is he that bleſſeth thee, and curſed is he that cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth thee:</hi> Num. 24, 6, 7, 9. This is the Lords doing in love to our
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:63183:18"/>King, and it is wonderfull in our ſight.</p>
            <p>The Star or coeleſtiall ſigne that appeared at the Nativity of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, was doubtleſs the Pleiades, [the name of the ſtar or ſigne ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing] of a moſt benigne and benevolent Aſpect, often mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Scripture, and of moſt ſweet influences, as appeareth by the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of holy truth, <hi>Job</hi> 38. and 31. ſometimes it is called <hi>Charles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waine,</hi> ſometimes the <hi>ſeven Stars;</hi> ſo it is named, <hi>Amos</hi> 15.8.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Plcides,</hi> ſome derive from plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality, <hi>quod</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>i. e. plures eſſent hyadibus rectius ex</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>or</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Navigando navigars, quod ſint utiles</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>i. e. Navigantibus.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are profitable, uſefull, propitious or proſperous to Navi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, Marriners, or Navigators. <hi>Quod primum Navigationis tempus orto ſuo graecis oftenderent; alii volunt
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:63183:19"/>eſſe, eas dictas quod</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>i. e. plure<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> quia ſunt ſeptem numero,</hi> ſeven in number: <hi>Alii à pleione matre nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natas affirmant;</hi> they were ſeven Siſters, the Daughters of <hi>Lygurgu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> or <hi>Atlas;</hi> They nouriſhed <hi>Bacchus</hi> and he afterwards tranſlated them into heaven, and are become the ſeven Stars, one of them is ſeldome ſeen, becauſe (as the Poets feign) all of them married Gods, and ſhe alone a mortall and obſcure man: <hi>Atlas</hi> was a skilful Aſtronomer, who gave the names of the ſeven daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, to theſe ſeven Stars compriſed in theſe verſes.</p>
            <q>
               <l>—Soptem eſſe feruntur,</l>
               <l>Quamvis ſunt oculis hominum, ſex obvia ſigna;</l>
               <l>Alcione Meropéque Electraque, Diva, Celano,</l>
               <l>Taygete, Sterope, Praeclaro lumine Maia.</l>
            </q>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:63183:19"/>
            <p>What can this ſignifie, but that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ur Soveraign <hi>Charls,</hi> is divinely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſigned (as <hi>Atlas</hi> is ſaid, to bear <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>p Heaven) to be a moſt firm Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r for ſupporting and promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing the glory of God, and good of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> is people in many Nations, the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>leiades</hi> ſignifying plurality, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>even the number of bleſſedneſſe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ee <hi>Gen.</hi> 28.13, 14, 15. the bleſſednes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>romiſed by God to <hi>Jacob.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe ſeven Stars are ſo placed, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t ternae quaeque ſtellae proxi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nae inter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> trigonon</hi> i. e. <hi>triquietram figuram, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>onſtituant,</hi> i. e. <hi>triangulum.</hi> That <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ach three ſtars next being them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>elves altogether do conſtitute, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ake a three ſquare, or triangle <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ometimes they are called, <hi>Triones,</hi> War, <hi>poſſunt Triones dici ſeptem, quod <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a ſitae stellae, ut terna trigonafaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt,</hi> ſeven Stars, or <hi>Charls waine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Several Obſervations may hence <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e probably deduced, as preſages
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:63183:20"/>conducing to his Majeſties futu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Progreſſe, to that tranſcendent h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> nour and exaltation, with which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> vine Providence is determined <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> dignifie a Prince ſo highly deſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, as our illuſtrious Soveraign<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>Why may we not believe th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> heavens have decreed, as well i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> creaſe of Honour and greatneſſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> this one perſon his Majeſty, as pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality of ſtars appearing, united i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to one ſigne, which in all prob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> bility ſhould ſignifie a larger exte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of Power, Dominion and Territ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries to the King, at whoſe Nativity they ſhined ſo brightly? Why ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not this heap of ſtars ſignifie acc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulation of Crowns, from a thre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> fold Throne, to a ſeven fold Scept<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> according to the number of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſtars? of which more hereafter.</p>
            <p>Why may we not ſuppoſe (ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Providence diſpoſed a ridd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for the Preachers Text, at the time of theſe ſtars apparition) that the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:63183:20"/>may be much myſtery, and many <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erets ſpecially conſiderable, and worthy the unfolding, lye hidden <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>et, which revealed, may happily five much ſatisfactory light to his Majeſties future proceedings? Our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſtrologers have faltred much, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd ſhot wondrous wide and moſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eakly failed in their predictions; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oneſt, learned and witty <hi>Wharton</hi> of any I obſerved) came neareſt to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e mark, when in <hi>Aprill,</hi> he cals for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Beeſome to ſweep the Houſe; <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd rid the Pallace both of Fox and Gooſe,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Aſtrology comes herein too ſhort <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o render a reſolution of this Riddle <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f <hi>Sampſon;</hi> a <hi>Joſeph</hi> or <hi>Daniel</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>inely inſpired will be requiſite for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſcovery of thoſe profound my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>teries, which divine Providence by Apparition of this celeſtial ſigne <hi>Pleiades</hi> at the birth of the King <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ath deſigned.</p>
            <p>Tis evident their influence hath
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:63183:21"/>operated upon his Majeſty very plainly in one particular (to wit) Navigation, being thereunto ſo much inclined, and therewith ſo much delighted, and having arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to ſo much knowledge therein, even to admiration of expert Navi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gators; this being but one branch of their effects, why may we not conclude all other their influences to attend his Majeſty propitiouſly?</p>
            <p>This propitious coeleſtiall ſigne, the <hi>Pleiades</hi> hath alſo another name, tis ſometimes called <hi>Charls waine,</hi> which ſeems to portend and ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie our Illuſtrious <hi>CHARLS,</hi> ſhall by glorious archievements gain the additional ſurname of <hi>Charls</hi> the great, become a ſecond <hi>Charlemaine,</hi> raiſe, rare Trophies of Renown to his perpetuall honour, riding tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphantly in the coeleſtial Charri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ot of reſplendent <hi>Charls</hi> his Waine, from the Weſtern and Northern bounds to the Eaſtern and Southern
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:63183:21"/>parts. <hi>Dilataberis ad orientem, &amp; oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridentem, &amp; Septentrionem, &amp; me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridiem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That prophetical Diſtick before <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ecited upon the apparition of this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>igne, intimatesas much:
<q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Magnus in occiduo Princeps jam na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcitur orbe,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>uctus &amp; Ecclipſis eras Orientis Erit.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>To the Weſtern world, a Prince is newly born,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And the Eaſt to morrow in Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clipſe ſhall mourn.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>This, (Ecclipſe, being a priva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion of light, ſignifies ſorrow, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>curity, adverſity, as light is an em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lem of Joy, Honour and Proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ity) preſaging the ſorrow con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eived in the Eaſtern parts, for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reat Conqueſts which our <hi>Charle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ain</hi> victoriouſly ſhal there obtain,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:63183:22"/>where his Majeſty ſhall appear, as a new Sun, riſing gloriouſly in the Orientall parts.</p>
            <p>In a ſhort Poem publiſhed in the year of our Lord 1635. is contained a continued ſucceſſion from King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond, there ſtiled the great <hi>Plantagenet,</hi> To our late ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Soveraign <hi>Charls le bon</hi> the firſt, with his Majeſties many anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent and lawfull titles to ſeveral for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Scepters (which I forbear at preſent to ſpecifie) therein alſo are many Prophetique expreſſions touching that royall, thrice renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Family, which by divine Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence may be fullfilled in our now moſt hopefull Soveraign (<hi>inter alia</hi>) take this into Conſideration, which to me ſeems not impertinent to our preſent purpoſe.</p>
            <q>
               <l>To him his Neighbour Potentates ſhall bend,</l>
               <l>The poplar Princes ſhall his vaſſals be</l>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:63183:22"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Affrick</hi> and <hi>India</hi> to him ſhall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents ſend;</l>
               <l>The <hi>Turk</hi> ſhall ſheath his raging Semiter,</l>
               <l>And proſtrate stoop unto his Amity,</l>
               <l>Esteeming them the happieſt which preferre,</l>
               <l>A league with him and ſo his name grow great</l>
               <l>As far as <hi>Neptunes</hi> wandring ſurges beat.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Another prediction touching the golden Mines and Indies, the diſcovery whereof <hi>Christopher Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mbus</hi> firſt offered to King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeventh, who married <hi>Elizabeth Plantagenet</hi> Daughter and heire of King <hi>Edward</hi> the Fourth, by which happy match the civill feud which long before between the houſes of <hi>York</hi> and <hi>Lancaſter</hi> remained, was reconciled.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:63183:23"/>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>Betwixt the Roſe which first grew in the wood,</l>
                  <l>And that which <hi>Venus</hi> coloured with her blood.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <bibl>Ovid Met.</bibl>
                  </l>
                  <l>She and her <hi>Richmond</hi> that thric<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> bleſſed paire,</l>
                  <l>Refuſed the Golden offer of Colone.</l>
                  <l>Becauſe they had a ſecret reed that one;</l>
                  <l>Who ſhould hereafter ſit in <hi>Arthurs</hi> Chaire.</l>
                  <l>Should fetch the Fleete when he occaſion ſaw,</l>
                  <l>And hold the golden Monarch in his aw.</l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>This prediction of our now ſover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aign King, then the Prince of great <hi>Britain,</hi> and the royall iſſue of our late pious King, and his moſt Serene Queen, <hi>Deuout Sans Dout,</hi> a <hi>Mary</hi> full of grace, pronouncing them both thrice bleſſed in their royall
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:63183:23"/>progeny, in this Diſtichon, not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together to be deſpiſed.</p>
            <p>Of the then Prince <hi>Charls</hi> now our King.</p>
            <q>
               <l>For he and they that ſhall of them deſcend.</l>
               <l>Shall raign in Britain till the world have end.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Why ſhould any Imagine theſe Predictions ſhall not attain accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment in his Majeſties Honour and happineſſe, ſeeing the King of Kings, owneth his Majeſty with ſo many ſignal tokens of love, and marks of Mercy, by diſpelling thoſe dark diſtructive clouds of bloudy Rebellion, turning his peoples hearts, as the Rivers of the South, making his Majeſty the delight, and deſire of thoſe people, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore deſpiſed him.</p>
            <p>Obſerve I pray this Prophetique preſage at hand, ready to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:63183:24"/>above 25. years ſince pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and publiſhed.</p>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>But turn our eyes, now from the clouded Weſt,</l>
                  <l>And ſee the new Sun riſing in the eaſt,</l>
                  <l>With what auſpicious brows the Heavens expreſt,</l>
                  <l>Their glad preſages, the coeleſtiall ſignes.</l>
                  <l>With holy anguries ſhined; <hi>Saturn</hi> did Feaſt</l>
                  <l>With ſprightly <hi>Jove,</hi> whilſt <hi>Apollo</hi> divines,</l>
                  <l>In delychick Raptures, the Age re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed again;</l>
                  <l>And takes new influence from bright <hi>Charles</hi> his <hi>Waine.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>Although theſe are but parcels of that Poem, touching the Royall line and Family of <hi>Plantaginet;</hi> yet ſome poeſie, hath ſometimes come ſo near to Prophecy, that as there is ſome vicinity in the names, ſo
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:63183:24"/>many times it happened in the matters of their writings. <hi>Propheta &amp; poeta,</hi> differ not much in the words; <hi>propheta</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which comes from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>praedico,</hi> ſignifies not only a Prophet, but alſo a Poet; And Poets have had another name, and that of Honour too, and that was <hi>Vates;</hi> How ſhall we diſtinguiſh between the Prophets and Poets of <hi>Iſrael?</hi> What are <hi>Jeremies</hi> thre in his <hi>Lamentations,</hi> but a kinde of <hi>Saphick Elegies? David</hi> Pſalms are not onely Poems, but Songs, ſnatches and raptures of a flaming ſpirit. The Jews had not two ſuch Kings in all their Catalogue, as <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> and his Father, P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ets both; There is a largeneſſe in their ſoules beyond the narrowneſs of other men; and why may we not then think, this may imbrace more both of Heaven and God, and they be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued with a Prophetique ſpirit.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:63183:25"/>
            <p>As Chriſts Star (for ſo it is term<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the wiſemen, <hi>Mat.</hi> 2.2.) ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing at his birth, was by St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine,</hi> called, <hi>magnifica lingua coeli,</hi> the glorious tongue of Heaven; So I hope without offence, the ſtar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that appeared at his Majeſties Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity may be ſtiled, <hi>Caroli meximi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Epiphania,</hi> the glorious ſtar, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtation of King <hi>Charles</hi> the great his exaltation. And as of Chriſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſtar (as ſome obſerve) It was no ordinary ſtar, <hi>Ex ſitu, mot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp; tempore lucendi,</hi> in reſpect of the ſite, motion and time of ſhining<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſo under favour may it be ſaid of the Kings ſtar, touching the <hi>temp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, 'twas extraordinary, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard other ſtars ſhine in the night, this at noon day, in the fight of the Sun, in its full glory; as it were<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> star</hi> appointed to wait on the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> hereby happily ſignifying, that the great <hi>Jehovah,</hi> the ſun of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe hath deſigned and elected our
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:63183:25"/>Soveraign KING, to be his High STEWARD, for management of the greateſt matters and affairs in his Family, in his Church and State, over his people, throughout a great part of the Univerſe; God giving his Majeſty ſuperiority over many other his ſervants, though ſeated in high places of Honour and power alſo.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Houdemius</hi> an Engliſhman, thus ſung of our Saviours ſtar.</p>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Novâ Caelum ſtellâ depingitur,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Dum Sol novus in terris Oritur.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Twas fit a new ſtar ſhould adorne the skies,</l>
                  <l>When a new Sun doth on the earth ariſe.</l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>In honour of our <hi>Charlemain,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Tis hop'd twil not be counted vain,</l>
                  <l>To frame according to this ſtrain,</l>
                  <l>A ſhort Ode, on bright <hi>Charls</hi> his Waine.</l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:63183:26"/>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Clarâ Caelum stel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>â depingitur,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Dum Rexclarus in terris oritur.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>Thus Engliſhed.</p>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>Why not a bright ſtar to adorn the ſkies,</l>
                  <l>When a Prince ſo bright, doth on the earth ariſe?</l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>Of that ſtar of Chriſt, it was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſied, <hi>Numbers</hi> 24.17. And of this ſtar of our King, by the ſame sybill that propheſied of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, as hereafter ſhall be ſhewed.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Stella luce vincens Luciferum.</l>
               <l>Magis ducit ad regem ſiderum.</l>
            </q>
            <p n="3">3. That ſtar of Chriſts ſerved to the Wiſemen, <hi>ad ducendum,</hi> to lead them to Chriſt; This of our King <hi>Charles</hi> ſerveth to us (if we will be wiſe) <hi>ad docendum,</hi> to teach and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct us in ready faithfull and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant obedience and loyalty, to <hi>Gods Vicegerent,</hi> our Leige Soveraigne; and from thence never to revolt, nor like broken bows ſtart aſide,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:63183:26"/>leaſt it ſhould happen unhappily to befall this Nation, as once it was ſpoken of <hi>Greece,</hi> in regard of the ruines (yea even of the utter di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, for <hi>etiam periere ruinae) Graeciam in Graecia quaerimus &amp; non invenimus;</hi> We fought for <hi>Greece</hi> in <hi>Greec.</hi> &amp; found it: let it never be ſaid of us, in regard of our recidiuall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loyalty, and diſobedience (I will not ſay rebellion.) <hi>Angliam in An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glia quaerimus &amp; non inventa eſt,</hi> we ſeek peace and plenty and ſafety in <hi>England,</hi> we ſeek that famous Church of <hi>England</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> but finde it not.</p>
            <p>The Coeleſtial ſign of the Pleiades, ſeven ſtars or <hi>Charles waine,</hi> whoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence ſignifies, higheſt exaltation, appearing brightly at Mid-day, whileſt the ſun ſhone in its glory, doth doubtles plainly demonſtrate, an ampler extent or enlargement of power, even from a threefold to a ſeven fold increaſe of Dominion
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:63183:27"/>and territory, to our moſt illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Charlemain;</hi> at whoſe Nativity this glorious ſigne appeared, which I ſhall endeavour by evident pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions of this nature more plainly to demonſtrate, producing the Judgment of ſome learned perſons (profoundly ſagacious in know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of ſecrets) touching other ſignes and ſtars long before, and ſome ſmce, all concurring and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing evidently to this purpoſe;
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The new star in Caſſiapeia,</hi> 1572.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The memorable blazing Star,</hi> 1610.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>That ſpeedy laſt Comet ſtella Crinita</hi> 9. <hi>of</hi> December 1652. <hi>ſudden ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance and motion violent,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>If we look into the Hiſtory of nature, and the times, or enquire in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſecrets of Stars, or obſerve the predictions of ſome perſons; of eminent knowledge in the Mathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matiques, we may finde matter ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient inducing us to believe that the time draweth near, and is even
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:63183:27"/>at hand, when as a miraculous Change in Kingdoms and Nations ſhall manifeſt it ſelf, in <hi>Europe,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the <hi>Northern</hi> and <hi>North-west,</hi> yea, and <hi>North-east</hi> people alſo, as ever did in any part of the world, fince the univerſal Deluge in <hi>Noahs</hi> time; and theſe ſo great and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midable actions, are to be perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by the Power and Atchiev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of one eminently excellent Perſon, whom God hath ordained for that purpoſe, to do wonders, whereſoever he ſhall come, both in Church and State.</p>
            <p>We may obſerve that as the firſt Empire of the world, was of the Aſſyrians, and began, or was feated in the Eaſt; that of the <hi>Perſians</hi> and <hi>Grecians</hi> in the South, and that of the <hi>Romanes</hi> in the Weſt; ſo tis moſt probable God hath determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, to raiſe up a Prince to an Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, Dominion or Principality of as great Splender, Majeſty, and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:63183:28"/>largeneſſe in the Northern parts, (if not exceeding any of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer) and to make him the moſt potent Prince in the terreſtrial U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſe; of whoſe ſurpaſſing might and extenſive greatneſſe; that new Star in <hi>Caſſiopeia</hi> (ſo called) 1572. was doubtleſſe the <hi>prodromus</hi> or forerunner; And this coeleſtial ſigne of the Pleiades <hi>May</hi> 29.1630. ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his birth, and preſageth his promiſing growth unto future greatneſs.</p>
            <p>For Confirmation of the credit hereof, that a mighty Monarch ſhall ariſe out of the North parts of <hi>Europe,</hi> let us conſider the Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie of <hi>Sybilla Titurtina,</hi> wherein ſhe ſpeakes plainly to this purpoſe; <hi>A Star ſhall ariſe in</hi> Europe, <hi>towards the great Houſe of the North, whoſe beams ſhall unexpectedly enlighten the whole world,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Siblla</hi> propheſied of Chriſt, in theſe words <hi>Naſcetur Christus in
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:63183:28"/>Bethlem;</hi> Chriſt ſhall be born in <hi>Bethlem. Annunciabitur in Nazareth,</hi> he ſhall be manifeſted in <hi>Nazareth. Regnante Tauro pacifico fundatore quietis;</hi> A pacifical Bull then raign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, being founder of peace; meant of <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar,</hi> in whoſe raign Chriſt Jeſus was born.</p>
            <p>If we ſhall diligently obſerve, the predictive judgment of ſome learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men, ſuppoſed to be induced with prophetique Spirits, who have long ſince and of latter times deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered their opinions touching this ſubject; we ſhall finde the reſult thereof, hath been to this purpoſe, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That the latter dayes or times might aſſuredly expect from the North, ſome glorious Star or Prince, who from thoſe parts of <hi>Furope</hi> ſhould ſuddenly burſt out, &amp; like a violent torrent, or ſuddain unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected prodigious Meteor, break his paſſage into the Southern, We<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtern
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:63183:29"/>and other parts of the World, with as much ſucceſſe and celerity in his undertakings, as attended that warlike <hi>Gracian,</hi> Prince <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> the great; at what time he not onely invaded, but alſo tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled down even to confuſion, the Perſian Monarchy or Dominion, which had ſtood firm (as Chrono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logers deliver 202.) years before.</p>
            <p>The Perſon they commonly ſtiled the Eagle of the North, the new Star of the North, or the Lyon of the North. This is neither No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vall, nor incredible, or improbable. For many learned of the <hi>Germaine</hi> and other Nations, for theſe laſt three Centuries of years, have been very diligent in the iniquiſition hereof, but more eſpecially from the year 1520. the point hath been controverted, and mens Expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions more impregnated, by reaſon of the prophecy of <hi>Sybilla Tiburtina,</hi> then diſcovered, engraven in anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ient
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:63183:29"/>Latine Characters, upon a Marble ſtone, anſwering the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ane</hi> language, 300. years before Chriſt, found in the bowels of mount <hi>Taurus</hi> upon a Deluge of Water which hapened in the Countrey of the <hi>Helvetians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Propheſie is thus Engliſhed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There ſhall ariſe a Star in <hi>Europe,</hi> over the Iberi, or Iberians, over or towards the great houſe of the North, whoſe beams ſhall unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectedly enlighten the whole world;</p>
            <p>This ſhall be in a moſt acceptable time, when as mortall men being wearied with War and Arms, ſhall unanimouſly be deſirous to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace peace.</p>
            <p>But at laſt the Of-ſpring of the moſt antient, or one of the antient progeny overcomes, and will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed on in a courſe of war, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:63183:30"/>
            <p>But <hi>France</hi> muſt firſt be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, or ſubject her ſelf to this Star, And <hi>Brittany</hi> in ſhips ſhall humbly caſt her ſelf at his knees, or mercy, imploring aſſiſtance from him.</p>
            <p>There are alſo in this <hi>Sybilla's</hi> Prophecy very many other materi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all predictions touching <hi>Italy,</hi> and other parts &amp; matters alſo, of moſt remarkable moment (the mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing whereof, at preſent I omit, and leave to ſome future opportunity) which doubtleſs in their appointed time will be verified; ſuch as are incredulous touching the truth of this Prophecy, if they be not reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vedly refractory, cannot but be convinced, by experimental effects, of ſuch parts thereof, as are already unqueſtionably fulfilled.</p>
            <p>This prophecy which lay ſo long obſcured, was no ſooner diſcover'd, but it was preſently tranſmitted by the Biſhop of <hi>Sedam,</hi> unto <hi>Charls</hi> King of <hi>Spain,</hi> elected-Emperour;
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:63183:30"/>he ſends it to the Pope, who imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately conveens together the moſt able Philoſophers and Aſtrologians in <hi>Italy,</hi> to give the interpretations thereof; theſe men to pleaſe the Pope and Emperour adjudged the Emperour <hi>Charls</hi> to be intended by the prophecy; but others more ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciouſly declared, the <hi>Iriſh</hi> nation and chief Ruler thereof, to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended thereby, as moſt probable in reſpect of the proximity of the word <hi>Iberi</hi> to <hi>Hiberni,</hi> which doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe was the true interpretation, as by the enſuing reaſons ſhall be more clearly manifeſted.</p>
            <p>Full fifty years after diſcovery thereof there appeared in <hi>Europe</hi> that miraculous new Star before mentioned in the year, 1572. in the Aſteriſm or Conſtellation of <hi>Caſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peia,</hi> at which time a Nobleman of <hi>Denmark,</hi> called <hi>Tycho Brahe,</hi> who being a very learned Aſtrologer, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and obſerving this new Star, its
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:63183:31"/>firſt appearance untill it ended, (It being as was prophecied, the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the whole world, becauſe it was fixed &amp; immoveable almoſt (ſixteen moneth) with rare large and exact Mathematicall Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, after peruſall of 30. ſeveral Authors and Books, written by men of ſeveralnations of the effects and quality of that new ſtar, him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf wrote a large Treatiſe thereof, and of his own accurate Obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Aſtrological predictions thereof; wherein (with much ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour) he mentions that prophecy of <hi>Sybilla Tiburtina</hi> terming it. <hi>Vati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinium hoc per ſe eſt admodum memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabile &amp; diligenti animadverſione dignum;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the judgement of this <hi>Tych<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Brahe,</hi> and many other of the moſt exquiſite Aſtronomers; This new ſtar ſeems by Divine Power, to be created as the fore-running hand maid or harbinger, to give the firſt
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:63183:31"/>manifeſtation or interpretation of his <hi>Sybill</hi>'s Prophecy, both whoſe unanimous concurrence made it evident, that the beginning of the moſt turbulent Changes in <hi>Europe,</hi> ſhould be occaſioned from the North; which parts (tis agreed by moſt) are intended not onely in the ſaid Prophecy, but alſo by that glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious new Star, and all other the Stars and Comets ſince appearing.</p>
            <p>This was ſuch a ſtar as no Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry relates the like. <hi>Hyperchus</hi> men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioneth one, two generations be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chriſt, which was not vertical to the Northern People, but this was verticall and appeared over their heads.</p>
            <p>Of this ſame opinion was <hi>Corne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius Gemma,</hi> in his Aſtrological judgements given upon this new Star, in his fecond book of Coſmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crit, printed 1575. p. 118. where he aſſignes theſe Countries to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the influence of that Coele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtial
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:63183:32"/>Star, <hi>viz. England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland, &amp;c. Grebnerus</hi> hath ſomewhat conducing to our pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, which ſhall hereafter be men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned.</p>
            <p>Concerning Wars, troubles, and Changes in theſe Countries, what hath come to paſſe, we need not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late the ſad experimental know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge thereof, doth ſufficiently ſhew and teſtifie; all <hi>Europe</hi> if not the whole world rings thereof. That which is principally aimed at i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> this ſhort Tract, is to demonſtrate the perſon intended in the ſaid pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie, and by the ſaid ſtar appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, 1572.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quarta ſeptentrialis ſive Borealis Monarchia, quam Deus constituit in ſeptentrione, per leonem Septentrio. nalem, magna cum admiratione illo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum aui Divinam Apocal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pſin &amp; Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monidm ill<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m, quam excer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o digiſa monstramus, &amp;c.</hi> The foure Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narches of the world are not by the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:63183:32"/>more profound Theologians, My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteriarches and Sagacious Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gians numbred, according to the Dominions of Kingdomes, as they have been in the world; but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the quarters of Heaven; And therefore they affirm, the fourth Monarchy of the World, ſhall be erected, ſeated and ſettled in the North by Divine Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, by means of the Lyon of the North, or Septrional Lyon, to the great admiration of thoſe that ſhall be then living, and ſhall rightly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the miſterious Harmony of matters contained in the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of St. <hi>John</hi> the Divine, and this Lyon of the North; at preſent (perhaps) they believing no ſuch thing.</p>
            <p>The effects of the ſaid Star 1572. draw near <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o manifeſtation, upon what Kingdome or Country the influence thereof ſhall be ſhewed; ſeveral and various have been the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:63183:33"/>judgements of many learned men, touching the perſon, place of being, time of his firſt appearance, and from what part or quarter of the heaven, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Ottoman</hi> or <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Empire (though abſolutely the greateſt now in the world) cannot be this Monarchy intended, nor the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour or King of <hi>Spain</hi> at or neer the time of apparition of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſtar born, or born ſince, or to be born in <hi>Spain</hi> or thoſe parts, is or can be judiciouſly infer'd to be the perſon born, to the great houſe of the North; by the ſaid <hi>Sybilla</hi> &amp; others intended, to be the Septronial Lyon (though happily the <hi>Ottoman</hi> and other Dominions, muſt in time be ſubdued by, and ſubjected to that great Houſe of the North) nor yet the King of <hi>Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> ſo ſtrenuouſly ſtood for, by ſome Aſtrologers, of our own Nation, but ſtrangely and miſerably, if not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciouſly miſtaken, as <hi>Ex ore &amp; pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:63183:33"/>ſuis propriis Judicetur,</hi> may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear from their own pens; their own writings being Judges, (ſome of which I have herein the rather recited, that the Conviction of their errors may be thence y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more evident) whoſe ignorance, envy, or unhappineſs, I know not, which is moſt to be condemned, who by their falſe calculations would en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour the tranſlation of proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and exaltation, from their own Leige Soveraign, to any other For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Prince or ſtranger, and rob their more worthily deſerving Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er of that juſt Right of Renown; which the great Creator hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordained, to dignifie that Perſon withall, which he hath determined to honour above others.</p>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:63183:34"/>
            <p>Tis not to be imagined, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, did or ever doth ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, ſuch miraculous Prophecies, or cauſe apparitions of ſuch new and ſtrange ſtars, at unuſuall times, to amaze or amuze mankinde, or to preſage no new or wonderfull changes in this inferiour world; In our <hi>Microcoſme,</hi> our <hi>Brittiſh</hi> Iſle, we have ſeen ſeverall ſad mutabilitie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in Civil and Eccleſiaſtical Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. But the ſweet influences of the Pleiades appearing at our Kings Nativity ſo gloriouſly, gives Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidence of operation thereof, according to this Aphoriſme: <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabuntur Reges, &amp; clara fiunt, &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ximè Rex illius clematis, quia creſce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> virtus &amp; Nobilitas ejus, &amp; populi &amp; vicini decorabunt eum regno ſuo, &amp; humiliabuntur ei, &amp; obedient ejus Mandatis.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:63183:34"/>
            <p>To what King or great Poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate in <hi>Europe,</hi> can this more aptly be applyed, then to our illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous King, whoſe name ſhall grow Great and Famous; and he ſhall increaſe in Vertue and Nobility, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And he and his people ſhall be glorious in the Eſteem of the World, and the neighbour Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſhall doe him honour, in his and their Territories, and ſeek and ſubmit unto him, obey his Orders and Commands, and count it an honour &amp; happineſs to be in League &amp; Favour with him.</p>
            <p>The many preceding even mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous Protections and Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances, from imminent and almoſt inevitable dangers wherewith his Majeſty hath been ſurrounded and circumvented, and the ineffa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Joy and Affections of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple for his Reſtoration, are clear Arguments and Teſtimonies of Gods great care and favouor to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his Majeſty. And that the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:63183:35"/>Heavens have pointed his Majeſty particularly to be that mighty Monarch predicted by the <hi>Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies</hi> and <hi>Stars</hi> afore ſpoken of.</p>
            <p>The Fate of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Family having ſtood 333 years or there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abouts, by moſt of the learnedſt Scrutators and Myſteriarches is drawing towards declenſion; The ſummers Sun of his proſperity is deſcending; the inſulting <hi>Sultan</hi> hath no happy ſtars attending his Fate; but violent Death, in a muti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous and tumultuous manner, by a ſeditious Souldiery or rebellious <hi>Janizaries</hi> (if credit may be given to <hi>Aſtrologers</hi>) is threatned to him. To be ſilent touching the <hi>Germane</hi> Emperor and Kings of <hi>Spain &amp; Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main,</hi> having very large portions of terreſtrial poſſeſſions, and the <hi>French</hi> King alſo; 'Tis conceived by men of judgement in the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thematicks not only the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Family but theſe alſo muſt bow to the Septentrionall Lyon.</p>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:63183:35"/>
            <p>Who this incomparable Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querer, which by ſome is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called the Eagle of the North, by ſome the Lyon of the North, and by ſome alſo the new Star of the North; who though this moſt magnificent Monarch (I ſay) is, or ſhall be, hath been and ſtill is by many ſagacious and curious inquiſitors and learned Men, alſo not onely in theſe but former times ſeriouſly controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, moſt concluding the name of this unparallel'd perſon to be <hi>Charls,</hi> of which opinion is <hi>Greb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerus;</hi> but ſome Aſtrologers of late times applying it and conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding earneſtly for <hi>Carolus Guſtavus</hi> the late King of <hi>Sweden,</hi> whoſe Death hath ſince ſufficiently con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced their errour therein; and ſurely to any not weakly, or wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſully blind, 'tis cleer as the Sun, by what hath been, and ſhall be herein ſaid, that our now King
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:63183:36"/>
               <hi>Charls</hi> is the very perſon intended by the ſaid <hi>Sybill's Propheſie,</hi> and the Star in <hi>Caſſiopeia;</hi> many very material parts of that <hi>Prophecy</hi> concerning his Majeſty being ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly already ful filled, and the reſt in Gods due time, (I dare en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage my Life) ſhall and will be accompliſhed.</p>
            <p>And ſeeing ſome have acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged <hi>Charls</hi> to be the name of this great perſon, though they doe not grant his Majeſty to be really that perſon; I ſhall humbly crave his Majeſties leave to offer hereafter ſome brief obſervations, touching his Majeſties Name, which happily may in ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects conduce to the clearing of the ſcruple touching the Perſon.</p>
            <p>I ſhall not herein pretend know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg in <hi>Aſtrologicall Predictians,</hi> nor preſume to the name <hi>of a Prophet,</hi> or <hi>the ſon</hi> of a <hi>Prophet;</hi> but to ſpeak with the <hi>Prophet Jeremy, It is a fire in
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:63183:36"/>my boues, and I cannot ſuppreſſe it.</hi> I have long ſince been and ſtill am preſſed in my ſpirit to declare what I conceive and believe God hath determined for Exaltation of his Majeſty, that unparrallel'd Prince, our <hi>Charlemain</hi> the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſaid Star 1572. may be ſaid to give the firſt ſignification to the ſaid <hi>Sybilla's</hi> Prophecy. But this celeſtiall Signe or Starre which appeared at the Birth of our now King of Great <hi>Britain,</hi> 1630. is an evident Manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and clear Confirmation of the fulfilling of that <hi>Prophecy,</hi> pointing out plainly our <hi>Charls</hi> the <hi>Second</hi> to be another <hi>Charle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main, Charls</hi> the <hi>Great,</hi> the very perſon in that <hi>Prophecy</hi> intended, and by Divine Providence preor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained to performe and accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh all thoſe admirable atchiev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and to attain that Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lative
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:63183:37"/>Greatneſſe and Exaltation therein predicted; even to be not only <hi>Carolus Maguus,</hi> but alſo <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rolus Maximus</hi> the Greateſt that hath been or ſhall be of that Name.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Carolus à Carolo, Grebnerus</hi> being in <hi>England</hi> with Queen <hi>Eliz.</hi> 1582. declared this as an undubitable Prophecy which ſhould after be fulfilled, <hi>deſcendens, &amp;c admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrabit imperium perfeliciſſime &amp; longe, late<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> dominabitur, &amp; major erit</hi> Carolo <hi>Magno;</hi> Our <hi>Charls le grand</hi> deſcending from <hi>Charls le bon,</hi> is undoubtedly that perſon, of which <hi>Grebner</hi> ſo prophecyeth. The Fathers goodneſſe is a firm Foundation for the Son's Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe The Fathers Piety, a ſure Ground-work for the Son's Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity. 'Tis ſaid of the late King that he was Crowned in White Robes to ſignifie his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polluted Integrity. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 112: 6.
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:63183:37"/>
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ro.</hi> 10.7. <hi>The Righteons ſhall be had in Everlaſting Remembrance; the Memoriall of the Juſt ſhall be bleſſed.</hi> If the Memory, ſurely the Polterity of the Juſt ſhall be bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; <hi>If the Righteous ſhall be like a Tree planted by the River ſide,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>whoſe leaf ſhall not wither; à for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiori,</hi> his fruit ſhall flouriſh and proſper.</p>
            <p>This pious Father prays for this Son's Goodneſſe rather then Greatneſſe, that he may be rather <hi>Charls le bon,</hi> the Good, then <hi>Charls le grand,</hi> the Great; God is pleaſed to hear his Prayer, as he did <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi>'s praying for Wiſdom only, and gives him Wealth, Honour and Greatneſſe alſo, in an Extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary manner; So will God give to our King, even give to his Majeſty not only goodneſſe, but greatneſſe alſo, deſtroy his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies out of his ſight, make him a great Name like unto the name of
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:63183:38"/>the great Men of the Earth, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous through the world, as he promiſed to <hi>David</hi> and to his ſeed after him, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.</p>
            <p>Our Soveraign <hi>Charls</hi> hath had a threefold ground for his Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. 1. Divine, Gods determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. 2. Paternall, a good Father. 3. Propheticall, The <hi>Sybills Prophecy;</hi> after that the Star in 1572. was a <hi>prodomus</hi> going before the <hi>Pleiades,</hi> which being a Sign Celeſtiall, was as a <hi>John</hi> Baptiſt or Precurſor, appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring at his Majeſties Nativity, to ſhew and certifie his Majeſty to be the very perſon by the ſaid Prophecy and Star predicted, in whom the effect of <hi>both</hi> was to be fullfilled: All theſe ſucceſſively preſaging Gods preordinate pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, of making his Majeſty <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rolus Maximus,</hi> that moſt Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificent Monarch of the North, which by the ſaid Prophecy and
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:63183:38"/>Star was prefigured, the great Lyon, and new Star of the North.</p>
            <p>Let us conſider the parts of the ſaid <hi>Prophecy,</hi> and we ſhall find it moſt properly, principally and ſolely applicable to our Soveraign <hi>Charls</hi> the <hi>Second,</hi> rather then to any other Prince or Potentate in the world.</p>
            <p>There ſhall ariſe a <hi>Star</hi> in <hi>Europe,</hi> over the <hi>Iberi</hi> or <hi>Iberians,</hi> over or towards the great houſe of the North, whoſe Beams ſhall Enligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten the whole world.</p>
            <p>In this Verſe are theſe 3. <hi>Points</hi> or <hi>Parts</hi> moſt conſiderable.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The place of the apparition of the <hi>Star.</hi> 2. Houſe or Family. 3. Future Glory or increaſe of Greatneſſe.</p>
            <p>In the year 1630, in the 110. year after the diſcovery of this <hi>Prophecy,</hi> and fifty Eight years after the new <hi>Stars</hi> manifeſtation which appeared 1572. on the 29.
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:63183:39"/>day of <hi>May,</hi> was our illuſtrious <hi>Charles</hi> borne in that very part of the World which both the old <hi>Prophecy</hi> and new <hi>Star</hi> deſigned, upon whoſe Nativity at Noon, the Sun then brightly ſhining appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the <hi>Pleiades,</hi> a celeſtial ſign full of ſweet influences called alſo his <hi>Charls Wain,</hi> as before is ſhewed, to ſignifie &amp; clearly to manifeſt to the world, That the Prince then born, was that great Star <hi>Sybilla</hi> inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; And the Star in 1572. to be but the <hi>Prodromus</hi> or precuiſor to this; And that by this God was pleaſed to demonſtrate the perſon intended by <hi>Sybills Prophecy;</hi> and to remove all Doubts and Scru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples which might ariſe touching the certainty thereof.</p>
            <p>Out of the words of the <hi>Prophecy</hi> it ſelf, 'tis evident, that our King <hi>Charles</hi> is the onely <hi>Perſon</hi> meant thereby; For whoſe is the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment? or who is over the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:63183:39"/>
               <hi>Iberi</hi> or <hi>Iberians,</hi> the <hi>Iriſh</hi> or <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> or for ſome hundreds of years have been, but his Royall Majeſty and Predeceſſours.</p>
            <p>Again, what great Houſe of the North is there in any part of <hi>Europe</hi> which is greater, or in reall truth ſo great, as our Soveraign, either in reſpect of antiquity, being for 500 years and more deſcended and continued and derived from the moſt Royall bloud, and Line of moſt renowned Kings as any in Chriſtendom, or the terrene world. Whether we conſider the <hi>Paternall</hi> or <hi>Maternall</hi> part of his Majeſties Kingly Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction, or in reſpect of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions and Territories <hi>de jure,</hi> belonging to his Majeſty, being an Empire of no mean power and Extent, not inferiour to the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt in <hi>Europe;</hi> and in regard of the moſt illuſtrious proweſſe, valour, and glorious atchievments of his
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:63183:40"/>Majeſties moſt heroicall famous Anceſtors and Predeceſſors.</p>
            <p>And as to the laſt part of this Verſe of the <hi>Prophecy,</hi> That the beams of that Star ſhall enlighten the whole world, that relateth to future Effects. But 'tis moſt evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that among all the higheſt humane Heroes, that Hiſtory mentioneth, none was ever ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured with the apparition of a celeſtiall Sign and Star at his Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity, Except our Saviour <hi>Chriſt</hi> and our Soveraign <hi>Charls,</hi> which doth clearly preſage great and wonderfull Acts to be performed by that perſon whoſe honour Heaven is determined to advance and make his Name and Fame glorious through the Univerſe; neither do we find any Celeſtiall ſign, Star or Planet, whoſe influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eace hath been honoured with ſo rare and excellent an <hi>Epitheton</hi> as God himſelf is pleas'd to attribute:
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:63183:40"/>in holy Writ to the <hi>Pleiades,</hi> ſeven <hi>Stars,</hi> or <hi>Charls's Wain,</hi> ſtiling the influences thereof ſweet and moſt mellifluous, ſhewing alſo the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſibility for any humane power to reſtrain the ſame, <hi>Job</hi> 38.31.</p>
            <p>The day of his Majeſties glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous renown now begins to dawn, And before the number of years which equalls the number of Stars in the ſaid Celeſtiall ſign <hi>Pleiades,</hi> appearing at his Majeſties Nativity, be expired, ſhall ſhine moſt brightly throughout <hi>Europe,</hi> and other parts more remote; yea, before a <hi>Trigon</hi> of that time be paſt, ſome fair foundation may be laid, for effecting of ſome Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous future Enterprizes, which with much celerity, will happily be accompliſhed. <q>Septem Stellae poſſunt dici triones, quod ita ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ae ſunt, ut terna trigona faciant.</q>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:63183:41"/>'Tis obſervable that this Star <hi>Pleiades</hi> or 7 <hi>Stars</hi> appeared about Noon, when the Sun in the <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridian</hi> ſhone gloriouſly; yet did not the glorious brightneſſe of the Sun, obſcure the light or appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance thereof, but rather add luſtre unto it, which may be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreted as an argument of the Heavens auſpicious aſpect upon his Majeſties undertakings, and that the Sun of Righteouſneſſe with healing under his wings will ſmile upon him, and ſhew the light of his Countenance upon his <hi>Enterprizes,</hi> and give thereunto happy ſucceſſes.</p>
            <p>This vernall Figure of Heaven promiſeth to his Majeſty ampli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of higheſt honour and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and that neither dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtique Conſpiracies, nor Forraign Oppoſitions ſhall be able to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent or reſtrain the ſweet and ſmiling Influences of the heavenly
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:63183:41"/>bodies, which promiſe him vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorious ſucceſſe.</p>
            <p>And happily it may not be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy our taking notice, that theſe <hi>Pleiades</hi> appear'd at Mid. day and in the ſpring, the Month of <hi>May</hi> the pleaſanteſt time of the Year, being that time and month of our Soveraigns Nativity; hence I obſerve that the Starrs ſignifie his Majeſties eminent appearance by divine deſignement, happeneth to be in or about the <hi>Meridian</hi> of his Age, the thirtieth year of his Majeſties Age, at which time his Majeſties coming, is with a ſweet &amp; comfortable Conqueſt of Love over his peoples Hearts, and 'tis well worth our joy and notice, that his Majeſty returns Trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phing, not ſo much over, as with his people; And I am confident his Majeſty conceives it a greater Honour and Felicity in ſaving theſe ſinking Kingdomes, then he
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:63183:42"/>would in gaining new ones; And that it is, yea and will be a greater content to his Majeſty, then any Plots of projecting councellors would have been, were they at the ends of their Deſigns. But this is the Lords doing, the work of the Divine hand; <hi>Digitus Dei,</hi> and 'tis wonderful in our Eyes, and ought to be wonderful joy and thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe in our Hearts.</p>
            <p>The number thirty, a <hi>trigonon</hi> of <hi>tenus</hi> is memorable for many myſteries being a <hi>trine</hi> of <hi>tenns, Ezekiall</hi> at the ſaid Age began to Prophecy, <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> was thirty years of Age when he began to preach in the Wilderneſſe and to prepare the wayes of the Lord. And in the Roman Church (wherein although <hi>non omnia,</hi> yet <hi>optima</hi> may be obſerved,) none are admitted to the Eccleſiaſtical fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction till thirty years of Age. 'Tis obſerved that <hi>Joſeph</hi> about the
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:63183:42"/>thirtieth year of his Age, was brought out of Priſon, and after his long Affliction and Impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment came to his great Honour, and received the Government from <hi>Pharaoh</hi> in <hi>Egypt, Moſes</hi> about the ſame time of his Age was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by God to lead the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> out of <hi>Egypt</hi> and to be their Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour. And <hi>David</hi> about that time of his Age came to the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome which God promiſed and gave him. And our Saviour Chriſt Jeſus, by S. <hi>John</hi> in <hi>Jordan,</hi> in the thirtieth year of his Age was Baptized, began to doe Miracles, and to teach the Kingdome of God; And after many ſufferings on Earth, not long after the thirti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth year of his Age, Aſcending into Heaven, ſitteth at the right hand of his Father who made his Enemies his Footſtoole, and had all Power and Dominion gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to him, being exalted from
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:63183:43"/>his Croſſe to his Crown of Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Glory.</p>
            <p>And as this was about the thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth year of his Age in his huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, ſo it was about the ſame time of the year alſo in the ſpring, <hi>Opima &amp; optima pars Anni</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſame time of Age, and of the year when our Saviours Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection and Aſcention came to paſſe, Divine Providence hath brought to paſſe, for our Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign King <hi>Charls</hi> his Reſtitution to his juſt Rights, and his Aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to his Royall Scepter and Crowne, and Throne, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the rage, and maugre the malice of all his Adverſaries; God hath ownd him as his <hi>David,</hi> his <hi>Dilectus,</hi> and ſaid, and done for him as he did for his beloved <hi>David; Yet have I ſet my King upon my holy hill of Sion,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.6. And his Majeſty may ſay with <hi>David; Ego autem conſtitutus ſum
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:63183:43"/>Rex ab eo ſuper montem ſanctum ejus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our Kings coming may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly be compared to the comfort of the <hi>Spring; Jam enim Hiems tranſtit, Imber abiit &amp; receſſit, flores apparuerunt in terra noſtra, Tempus avium Cantationis advenit, vex tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turis andita in terra noſtra: ficus protulit groſſos ſuos, vineae florentes dederunt odorem,</hi> Cant. 2.11, 12. The Winter of our wofull Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage and Affliction is paſſed over; the ſhowers of our ſorrow and oppreſſion are blown away, and the clouds of our calamities, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled and diſperſed, by the bright ſun of Soveraign's ſhining, whoſe enlivening influence re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vives the State, and makes it flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh; the fragrant flowers of Comfort appear in the garden of our Lands: The voice of the Turtle, Unity and Peace, is heard in our land; we may ſit ſafely
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:63183:44"/>under our Vines, &amp; eat the Fruits of our Fig trees.</p>
            <p>The Antient Romans uſed <hi>ver ſacrum facere</hi> to hallow the ſpring to God, and the Primitive Church Conſecrated the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the year to God.</p>
            <p>The time of our Soveraigns reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution to his Crown and Dignity being in the ſpring, and in <hi>May Menſis Florum,</hi> the moſt Fragrant and ſweeteſt Month of the Year, (the vertue and quinteſſence of all Herbs, Flowers and Plants, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing then in their full force) which ſome derive a <hi>Majoribus,</hi> others a <hi>Maio, i.e. Jupiter</hi> which may ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie the ſweet influences &amp; effects of the <hi>Pleiades</hi> or <hi>Charls</hi>'s Wain, attracting the Hearts and affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of his people in a moſt Loyall and Loving manner towards his Majeſty; and promiſing gracious and happy ſucceſſe to all his future undertakings.</p>
            <pb n="69" facs="tcp:63183:44"/>
            <p>But to return to the further con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of the ſaid Prophecy of <hi>Sybilla;</hi> the Star was prophecyed to appear in a moſt acceptable time, when as mortal men being wearied with War, and Arms, ſhall Unanimouſly deſire to Embrace peace. This part of the Prophcy is fulfilled perfectly, wherein we may take notice of Divine Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, taking all occaſions and opportunities of time to do for perſons whom God determineth to promote and advance, and to prevent danger that may befall them, as now appears by his Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy ſhewed to the Kings Majeſty, beyond all humane expectation in ſo wonderfully delivering his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty from both Domeſtick and Foreign Perils, and preſerving him to be the Joy and Delight of his people.</p>
            <p>To proceed to the verſe or part of the Prophecy where tis ſaid,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:63183:45"/>but at length the off-ſpring of the moſt ancient, or one of the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Progeny overcomes: This ſheweth by what hath been ſaid before, that this part of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy cannot be intended not applyed to any other then his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, being the Off-ſpring of the Blood Royall of the Kings of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> and next Heir to theſe Crowns.</p>
            <p>The next thing offering it ſelf to Conſideration, is this; in the ſaid Prophecy it follows thus, but <hi>France</hi> muſt firſt be overcome o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſubject her ſelf to this ſtar; &amp; <hi>Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tany</hi> in ſhips ſhall humbly caſt her ſelf at his knees for mercy, implo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring aſſiſtance from him.</p>
            <p>Touching the former part o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> this verſe or particle of the ſaid Prophecy ſomewhat might be truly ſaid concerning the right of that Crown and Kingdome, to whom it belongs.</p>
            <pb n="71" facs="tcp:63183:45"/>
            <p>But I ſhall not preſume to preſs or ſay any thing concerning that, but take the Poets expreſſion for a premonition.
<q>
                  <l>(Cum Canerem Reges &amp; Praelia Cyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thius aurem</l>
                  <l>—vellit.</l>
               </q> And reſt ſatisfied with that ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>quae ſupra nos nihil ad nos,</hi> His Majeſty is Wiſe and Valiant, and when Gods appointed time ſhall come, the Divine hand will reſtore to his Majeſty thoſe Dominions which his Divine Majeſty hath determined for his Enjoyment; as he hath to thoſe of great <hi>Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain</hi> and <hi>Ireland;</hi> which leads me to the latter part of the verſe of this Prophecy.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Brittany</hi> in ſhips ſhall hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly caſt her ſelf at his Knees or Mercy imploring aſſiſtance from him; how perfectly this is fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, ther's none ſurely ſo blind or
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:63183:46"/>impudent, as to deny the accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment hereof: and thoſe Aſtrologers of our Nation who have heretofore, either infirmly, impudently, or impiouſly oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the application of this <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy,</hi> to our preſent ſacred So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign, (whom God hath in ſo ſignall a manner ſeverall waies eminently owned as his King, his Vice-gerent on Earth) will be clearly connced by theſe evident accompliſhments of the moſt materiall parts of this <hi>Prophecy;</hi> and with all ſubmiſſive acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement confeſſe their Errours and Ignorance; and humbly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plore Gods, the Kings and the peoples pardon, for their falſe malevolent calculations and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitful deluſions in denying Gods divine Decrees, detracting from his Majeſties true honor, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luding the people: And in all humility, acknowledge his Majeſty, our Soveraign Lord
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:63183:46"/>
               <hi>Charls</hi> the <hi>Second,</hi> to be that perſon intended by the ſaid <hi>Prophecy,</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaged by the ſaid Star in 1572; confirmed by that celeſtiall ſign appearing at his Birth, the <hi>Pleiades;</hi> whoſe ſweet influences have in ſeveral reſpects plainly appeared, And will attribute (as juſtly due to his Majeſty) that ſtile and title of Eagle of the North, New <hi>Star</hi> of the North, <hi>Lyon</hi> of the North; ſole Monarch of the fourth Monarchy Septentrionall, to be ſettled and ſeated in the North. The Septentrional Lyon being ſignified by his Majeſties Star of Nativity, the <hi>Pleiades;</hi> and alſo by the Kings Armes both of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> both bearing Lyons, <hi>England</hi> three Lyons paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, and <hi>Scotland</hi> the Lyon Ram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pant. And <hi>Septentrio,</hi> ſignifying the North Star being the ſame with his Majeſties Birth-Star; <hi>ſcilicet ſidus ex ſeptem ſtellis quae
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:63183:47"/>Triones dicuntur;</hi> And <hi>Sidus</hi> being derived <hi>ex</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ex</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>quod plures ſimul videntur; vel quod fit plurium ſtellarum conventus: vel ex ſeder,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>ordo, ſignificat enim ordines ſtellarum;</hi> the <hi>Pleiades,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Conventus 7<hi rend="sup">em</hi> ſtellarum, quae ita ordine ſunt ſitae, ut ternae quaeque ſtellae proximae inter ſe trigonon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituunt,</hi> meaning thereby his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties three-fold preſent diadem or Dominion to be amplified to a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ld.</p>
            <p>And as Divine Providence had ſo preordained, that the Preachers Text at the time of the appearing of that Star ſhould be a Riddle; ſo doubtleſſe many myſterious ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets &amp; obſervations may be from the 7n. Stars deduced; the moſt Myſterious numbers of three and ſeven, ſeven Stars ſo placed toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that every three next make a <hi>Trigonon,</hi> or three quarter trian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular, or three ſquare figur escom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>prehended in the word or ſign <hi>Septentrio, ſeptem Triones</hi> or
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:63183:47"/>
               <hi>ter ſeptem</hi> ſignifying perhaps his Majeſties firſt action in the 21 year of his Age; wherein divine Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance with Honour appeared. The <hi>Pleiades</hi> Miniſtring plentifull matter of ſerious conſideration, which I ſhall leave to ſome other opportunity; For although his Maje. prevailed not in the firſt at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, yet a dark and cloudy mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning may and did preſage a bright Sun-ſhine day of a more happy Conqueſt to enſue without blood even over the hearts of his people.</p>
            <p>Our now moſt gracious King is the 3d. Monarch of great <hi>Britain,</hi> and the 3d. Prince of <hi>Wales</hi> of the name <hi>Charles,</hi> though the ſecond King of that name; into this Prince happily Divine Providence hath determined to infuſe all the vertues and powers of his Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, the former Monarchs and Princes of theſe Nations, and to make his Majeſty more eminently
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:63183:48"/>glorious and famous then any or either of thoſe, or of his former Predeceſſors, and out of a three-old Dominion or Diadem; to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large his Territories to a ſeven-fold Empire, which by the ſeven Stars ſeems to be ſignified.</p>
            <p>What means that following part of the <hi>Sybills</hi> Prophecy in theſe words: <hi>Italy</hi> pawſing with great difficulty about theſe trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſome Governments, and Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, will ſignifie her right hand unto him, meaning the Star of the great houſe of the <hi>North:</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Rome</hi> ſtanding on ſeven Hills be intended for the right hand of <hi>Italy,</hi> in the Prophecy it matters not? 'Tis not improbable to be believed, that our <hi>Carolus Maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi> aſſiſting the Chriſtian, ſhall extend his Empire into the <hi>Mahu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metan Territories.</hi> I dare engage my life our <hi>Charle-main</hi> into a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven-fold Soveraignty of Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:63183:48"/>Rides triumphant in his Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ot of incomparable conqueſts, elſe what means <hi>Charls</hi> his Wain? ſeven Stars or <hi>Peliades?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The number Seven is a number of various and manifold power; if we conſider the ſeveral parts thereof, and the joyning together of them, we ſhall confeſſe as well by the joyning as by its fullneſſe apart, that it is moſt full of Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty: The <hi>Pythagorians</hi> call it <hi>ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hiculum vitae,</hi> becauſe it contains Body and Soul. The body con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting of four Elements, and the number three reſpects the ſoul in its three-fold power, rationall, iraſcible and concupiſcible; ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven conſiſting of 3 and 4. This number (as ſome learned Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers affirm) joyning the ſoul to the body; the vertue hereof relates to the generation of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, and cauſeth Man to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, formed, brought forth
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:63183:49"/>nouriſhed, live, and indeed alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether to ſubſiſt, as by many par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars (too long to relate) might be proved.</p>
            <p>It is moſt evident our <hi>Charlemain</hi> is the <hi>vehiculum vitae</hi> of theſe three Nations; the onely ſupporting <hi>Atlas</hi> of the State, <hi>quaſi divinitus ortus</hi> the prime and principall Pillar of the ſafety and welfare of theſe three Kingdoms.
<q>
                  <l>Carolus, alter ut Atlas eſt, divinitus ortus,</l>
                  <l>Hic humeris Coelum ſuſtinet, ille Statum.</l>
               </q> There is alſo in Celeſtials a moſt potent power of this number 7; There are four corners of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven diametrically looking one towards the other, which is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted a moſt full and powerfull aſpect, and conſiſts of the number ſeven; For it is made from the ſeventh ſign, and makes a croſs, the moſt powerfull figure of all:
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:63183:49"/>By the ſame radiation and num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the Solſtice is diſtant from Winter and the Winter aequino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiall from Summer; all which are done by ſeven Stars: there are ſeven Circles in Heaven ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the longitude of the axletree; there are ſeven Stars greater or leſſer, about the Artick pole, called <hi>Charles wain;</hi> ſeven Stars called the <hi>Pleiades,</hi> ſeven <hi>Planets,</hi> according to ſeven dayes conſtituting weeks. Why may not the principal and moſt proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous powers of thoſe ſeven <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets,</hi> by the Influence of the ſeven Stars of the Artick pole <hi>Charles wain,</hi> and the <hi>Pleiades,</hi> be ſignified, to have their influences and ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations upon the actions and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings of our great Septentrio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Star (who for his prudence, valour and piety (which is the beſt policy) may be truly termed the Lyon of the North or great Northern Monarch.</p>
            <pb n="80" facs="tcp:63183:50"/>
            <p>It is alſo applyed to <hi>Saturn, Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netarum primus deorum antiquiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi> which aſcending from the lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer is the 7th. Planet; which be tokens reſt, to which the ſeventh day is aſcribed (on which our <hi>Charlemain</hi> was born as before is ſhewed preſaging reſt to theſe Nations during his Majeſties Reign;) which ſignifies the ſeven thouſandth, <hi>Wherein</hi> (as St. <hi>John</hi> in the <hi>Revelation</hi> witneſſeth) <hi>the Dragon, which is the Divell, and Satan, being bound, men ſhall be quiet and lead a peaceable Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Why may not this be applyed to the time of the Reign of our <hi>Charlemain</hi> the Second? The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth day, the Creatour reſted from his work, wherefore this day was by <hi>Moſes</hi> called the Sabboth, <hi>(i.e.)</hi> The day of reſt; hence it was that Chriſt reſted the ſeventh day in the Grave. This number hath alſo a great Communion with the Croſſe; as alſo with
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:63183:50"/>Chriſt in whom is all our bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, reſt and felicity.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Pythagorians</hi> call it the number of Virginity, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they dedicated it to <hi>Pallas</hi> the ſeigned Goddeſs of Chaſtity.</p>
            <p>It hath alſo in Religion moſt potent ſignes of its Eſteem; and is called the number of an Oath. Hence among the <hi>Hebrews</hi> to ſwear is called <hi>Septenary, (i.e.)</hi> to proteſt by 7: ſo <hi>Abraham</hi> when he made a Covenant with <hi>Abime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lech</hi> appointed ſeven Ewe Lambs for a Teſtimony.</p>
            <p>It is alſo called the number of bleſſedneſs whence that, <q>O terque quaterque Beatus!</q> O thrice and fourtimes bleſſed! Hence the <hi>Pleiades</hi> a celeſtial ſign, coacted and compounded of ſeven Stars may be ſaid to preſage a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven-fold bleſſedneſſe to our Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign <hi>King Charles;</hi> upon whoſe Birth it appeared, &amp; thoſe 7 beati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:63183:51"/>in the 5th. of St. <hi>Matthew</hi> to be conferr'd upon his Majeſty; Some Roman Authors ſeem to affirm, that the Star appearing upon the Birth of our Saviour was not a ſingular but an heap of Stars, deducing their opinion from one, <hi>Albumuzar an Arabian,</hi> Phiſitian, &amp; Aſtrologer averring it to be that ſign in the Zodiak calld <hi>virgo,</hi> the wich virgin is compoſed of ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Stars as may aptly pourtray, <hi>Virginem, geſtantem inter brachia filium,</hi> a Virgin bearing an infant in her Armes, and ſo have thought that to be this Star; perhaps from the Prophecy of our <hi>Sybilla Tibur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tina,</hi> who when <hi>Auguſtus</hi> boaſted of his ſuper-human Majeſty, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him <hi>Virginem in caelo infantem portantem.</hi> A <hi>Virgin</hi> in heaven bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring a young Child in her Arms; in theſe words <hi>hic puer Major eſt te, ipſum adora;</hi> Yonder infant is greater then thou art, O <hi>Caeſar</hi>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:63183:51"/>worſhip him, to this St. <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom</hi> is produced as a witneſs who ſays thus; this Star appeared to them deſcending upon that vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorial Mountain having in it th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> form of a little Child, and above him the ſimilitude of a Croſſe.</p>
            <p>What credit may be given to thoſe opinions I diſpu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e not, the Morall and Divine applications thereof may be profitable for the ſpiritual health of the Soul touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Faith in Chriſt our Saviour; but tis moſt probable, that by this heap of Stars at his Majeſties Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity appearing, heaps of happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs &amp; accumulation of comforts are ſurely preſaged to his Majeſty and all his faithful liedge people in &amp; through his bleſſed Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and by plurality of Stars Celeſtiall, plurality of proſperity to the State terreſtriall under his Majeſties Dominion.</p>
            <p>That thoſe Obſervations tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:63183:52"/>the Numbers of 3 and 7. in the <hi>Pleiades,</hi> ſeven <hi>Stars</hi> or <hi>Charls wain,</hi> and other numbers (whereof mention before is or may be here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after made) may not be thought tedious or impertinent; It will not be unworthy our taking no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, that as amongſt the Celeſtiall <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the <hi>Stars</hi> of Heaven are reckoned among the moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Characters of the Divinity, Power, wiſdome and Glory of the Creator, in that they are written and engraven with the finger of God himſelfe (the Father of Lights;) <hi>Quibus inviſibilia Dei intelliguntur, ac providentur, ipſa<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> aeterna ejus potentia, quibus gloria Dei enarratur:</hi> So not onely the moſt eminent Philoſophers do unanimouſly teach, but alſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Catholique Divine Doctors eſpecially <hi>Hierom, Auſtin, Origen, Ambroſe, Gregory Nazianzen, Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſius, Bede,</hi> and many more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:63183:52"/>That there lies wonderfull Efficacy and rare Vertue in Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers. <hi>Severinus Boethius</hi> ſaith, that all things which were firſt made by the nature of things in the firſt Age, ſeem to be formed by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of Numbers; for this was the principall pattern in the mind of the Creator. Hence is bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed the number of Elements, hence the courſes of Times, hence the motion of the Stars, and the revolution of the Heaven and the ſtate of all things ſubſiſt by the uniting together of Numbers; which are therefore endowed with great and ſublime vertues. All ſpecies of natural and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural things are joined together by certaine Numbers; which made <hi>Pythagoras</hi> ſay, that Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber is that by which all things conſiſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If there be ſo many great and occu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vertues in natural things of
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:63183:53"/>manifeſt operations, It is no won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that there ſhould be in Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers much Greater and more oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult, and alſo more wonderfull and efficacious; Foraſmuch as they are more formall, more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and naturally in the celeſtials, not mixt with ſeparated ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances; but having the greateſt and moſt ſimple commixion with the Idaea's in the mind of God, from which they receive their proper and moſt efficacious ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues; and ſo are of moſt force and conduce moſt to the obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of ſpiritual and divine Gifts. <hi>Proclus</hi> ſaith, that number hath alwaies a being: yet there is ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral ſorts of Natures of Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers; there is one in voice, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the proportion of them, another in the Soul and Reaſon, and another in Divine things.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Themiſtius Boethius,</hi> and <hi>Aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rois</hi> the <hi>Babylonian,</hi> together with
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:63183:53"/>
               <hi>Plato,</hi> do ſo extol numbers, that they think no man can be a true Philoſopher without them. But they ſpeak of a rationall and formall number, not of a mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall, ſenſible or vocall, the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Merchants, buying and ſelling; of which the <hi>Pythagori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, Platoniſts,</hi> and <hi>Auſtin</hi> make no reckoning, but apply it to the proportion reſulting from it, which number they call natural, rationall, formall, from which great myſteries flow, as well as in natural, as divine heavenly things. By this (ſay theſe and other profound <hi>Philoſophers</hi>) is there a way made, for the ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching out and underſtanding of all things knowable. By it the next acceſſe to naturall prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cying is had; and the <hi>Abbot Joachim</hi> proceeded no other ways in his prophecies, but by forma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> numbers.</p>
            <pb n="88" facs="tcp:63183:54"/>
            <p>This Digeſſion is made on purpoſe, if it may be to prevent thoſe Objections which may be raiſed againſt Obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons upon Numbers, wherein (if ſome of the moſt Learned not onely Philoſophers, but di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines may be believed) are many occult vertues, and diſtinct my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries both divine and naturall; But it muſt be remembred that what hath been ſaid touching numbers or ſhall be ſaid touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the powers thereof, is not meant of vocal or Merchants numbers, but of rational, formal and natural; But ſome divine and philoſophical Authors af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, that he which knows how to join together the vocal num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, and natural with divine, and order them into ſome har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, may happily be able to know and work wonderfull things by numbers. T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ytha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorians</hi>
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:63183:54"/>profeſſe they can prog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſticate many things by the numbers of Names; In which truly, if there did not lie a great Myſtery, why hath St. <hi>John</hi> in the Revelation ſaid <hi>Cap.</hi> 13.17.18. <hi>Hîc ſapientia eſt, qui habet intelle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum computet numerum beſtiae, nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merus enim hominis eſt.</hi> He which hath underſtanding let him compute the number of the name of the Beaſt, which is the number of a man; And this was the moſt famous manner of computing amongſt the <hi>Hebrews</hi> and <hi>Cabaliſts;</hi> and happily may be at this day in theſe times, a more certain way and courſe for conjecturall calculations, then many, yea moſt of our late A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrologers have found out, at leſt expoſed to publick teſt; whoſe miſerable miſtakes and groſſe Errors, have ſomewhat impea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched the reputation of their ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:63183:55"/>and left ſome blemiſh upon ſome of the reputed principal profeſſors thereof, which I ſpare to ſpecifie, chooſing ſilence rather then taunting aſperſions, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that although tis ſaid and ſo the verſe begins with <hi>aſtra re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gunt homines,</hi> yet it concludes thus, <hi>ſed regit aſtra Deus,</hi> and what mortal is there, that keeps the key of the Almighties Cabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net, or hath known his mind; and conſidering as a man, that <hi>Humanum eſt Errare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to return to the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the number Seven, the number of his Majeſties Nativi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Star, a number of ſuch vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and manyfold vertue and power, That to expreſſe the ſame would require a large ſingle volume by it ſelf. Somewhat hath been ſaid before hereof, which I ſhall not repeat, but proceed with all brevity to ſet down ſome ſhort obſervations
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:63183:55"/>on that, and the number three and ſome other numbers oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunely offered to conſideration on this preſent occaſion.</p>
            <p>Seven is a number of purificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Eliſha</hi> the Prophet bid leprous <hi>Naaman</hi> waſh ſeven times in <hi>Jor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dan</hi> which done he was clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and the Leprous perſon un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the law that was to be clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed was ſprinkled ſeven times with the blood of a Sparrow. The Leproſie of Rebellion in theſe Nations, needs 7 fold clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings for purification. It is a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of repentance and remiſſion, protending the peoples peniten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial ſubmiſſion, and our Kings gracious Remiſſion. Tis a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of liberty, according to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> law, where each <hi>Hebrew</hi> ſervant the ſeventh year claimed Liberty may mind the King of a Jubile; 'tis ſuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to divine praiſes the ſanctify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Lords day, and people by praiſes &amp; prayers as ſaith the
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:63183:56"/>Prophet ſeven times a day do I praiſe thee, ſhewing his gratitude for Gods goodneſs, &amp;c. A good pattern for a pious K. tis a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of revenge, as in Scripture of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten appears, <hi>Cain</hi> ſhall be reveng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed 7ld. &amp; the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſaith, <hi>ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Neighbors ſeven-fold into their boſom, their reproach,</hi> &amp;c. Signi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying his Majeſty ſhall be ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled to take a ſeven-fold revenge of his Enemies, God will give power ſo to do. Tis a number conſecrated to the Holy Ghoſt, which the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes to be ſeven-fold accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his gifts (<hi>viz.</hi>) the ſpirit of wiſdom and underſtanding, the ſpirit of council and ſtrength, the ſpirit of knowledge and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, and the ſpirit of the fear of the Lord, which we read in <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charia</hi> to be the 7 Eyes of God, why may we not conceive that, <hi>Hereby is noted the manifold rare Gifts where with his Majeſty is
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:63183:56"/>and ſhall be endowed from Heaven and the favourable Countenance of the Lord looking towards him, ſhin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing graciouſly upon him?</hi> In the book of the <hi>Revelation</hi> we may read of ſeven Angels ſpirits ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in the preſence of God, and ſeven Lamps burning before the throne of God, and ſeven Gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Candleſticks, and in the middle thereof was <hi>one like the Son of man,</hi> and he had in his right hand ſeven Stars. What is it not plain and proper, that by the Son of man is our Saviour, &amp; by the ſeven Stars our Soveraign intended? our King in the hand of our God? what other or better interpretation, in relation to his Maje. by way of parallel from the <hi>Pleiades</hi> can be made, but that Gods Divine Majeſty will gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly give unto our King a 7<hi rend="sup">ld</hi>. attendance and guard of Holy Angels, his miniſtring ſpirits, to protect his princely perſon from
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:63183:57"/>all eminent dangers: the burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Lamps and Golden Candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticks, and one like the Son of man, with ſeven Stars in his right hand, what application can be made hereof, but that the Son of righteouſneſſe with healing under his wings will guide his Majeſty through the wilderneſſe of this wretched world, lead him through the dark deſerts of dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, as he did the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> day and night, by a cloud and pillar of fire; illuminate his under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding to ſee the wondrous things of Divine Laws, and give him a large portion of wiſdome for humane Government; and that Almighty God will ſo guide the King with his right hand, that he ſhall not daſh his foot againſt a ſtone: the ſeven Stars being the Celeſtiall ſign at the Kings Nativity, may ſignifie the King to be the perſon, the Sidus of ſeven Stars ſaid to be in
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:63183:57"/>the right hand of the Sonne of Man, where is protection and ſafety infallible under the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of the ſacred wings of the omnipotent. Now by what hath been ſaid it is apparent, that the number ſeven among all the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther numbers may deſervedly be ſaid to be moſt full of all efficacy: more over this number ſeven hath great conformity with the number twelve, for as three and four make ſeven, ſo thrice four makes twelve, which are the numbers of the Celeſtial Planets and Signes reſulting from the ſame Root, and by the number three partaking of the Divinity and by the number four of the nature of Elements and other inferiour things.</p>
            <p>There is in ſacred Writ, a very great Obſervance of this num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber ſeven before all others, and many and very great are the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries thereof, many have been
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:63183:58"/>already reckoned up and many more might be repeated out of holy Writ, by which it may ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily appear that the number 7, doth ſignifie a certain fullneſſe of ſacred Myſteries: what an admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and unparrallel'd perſon may we then hope and expect that to be, whoſe arrival on earth ſuch a glorious myſterious num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, not of terreſtrial, but celeſtial bodies, are ſent to celebrate and congratulate; ſurely God was pleaſed to ſend theſe heavenly Heralds to proclame this <hi>Prince</hi> to be in time convenient to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Deſignment, the moſt pious, proſperous and puiſſant <hi>Prince</hi> in <hi>Europe;</hi> Nay, is it not moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, that divine providence hath determined to make that perſon ſuperlatively Excellent, whoſe Entertainment the King of Kings is pleaſed to Dignifie with the Attendance of ſuch
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:63183:58"/>heavenly harbingers, and anſpioi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Ambaſſadors, who are praemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed on purpoſe to premon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rate and promulgate to the world, the Nativity, Apparition, and coming of the mightieſt Monarch in the terrene Univerſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dion</hi> writes of a <hi>Phaenix</hi> that was ſeen before the laſt year of <hi>Tiberius</hi> which <hi>Byrd</hi> is a perfect Emblem of the Reſurrection, and ſignified that at that time Chriſt roſe from the dead, and the Goſpell was then to be ſpread abroad, which is an aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeveration of the dead riſing again, of the reſurrection, which the ſlee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Sadduces denyed.</p>
            <p>If there be <hi>Phoenix,</hi> tis our King, of this Age, cauſing a Reſurrection of theſe Nations from their Graves of Ruine and Slavery, to rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing and liberty.</p>
            <p>What did the Favour worn by the people before the Kings com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in commonly called the Kings
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:63183:59"/>colors; <hi>de phoeniceo colore,</hi> of a phae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nician, crimſon, or <hi>purpureo,</hi> a purple colour ſignifies: what did that por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend? but that our <hi>Phoenix,</hi> ſhould return triumphing; and be anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the oyle of gladneſſe, and that God through his Majeſties Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment ſhould recover both Church and State from eminent ruine, give us beauty for aſhes, and the garment of gladnes, for the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of heavineſſe.</p>
            <p>Thoſe inconſiderable ſeeming ſignes of wearing the Kings Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, the <hi>Phoenix</hi> colours; howe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver not noted, proves to be a plain prediction of the Kings and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries Reſtitution and Reſurrection: when God hath a purpoſe to bring to paſſe any thing, be it ever ſo great, the meaneſt means is not to be diſpiſed, nor any the leaſt omen to be contemned. <hi>Ex parvis prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipiis ad ſummum ſaepe pervenitur.</hi> Smal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d ſad beginnings, God of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:63183:59"/>brings to glad and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous perfection, who hath deſpiſed the day of ſmal things, <hi>Zach.</hi> 4.10. Out of the aſhes of that pious, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient, prudent <hi>Phoenix, Charls</hi> the I. hath God raiſed for us another <hi>Phoenix.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Phoenix</hi> as <hi>Pliny</hi> hath it, takes her name, <hi>ex phoeniceo pennae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum colore, nomen invenit;</hi> from the colour of the <hi>Phoenix</hi> wings or fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>el à palmae Genere,</hi> from a kinde of Palm tree; <hi>quae <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> dici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. Morientis &amp; renaſcentis ram<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> figura.</hi> The emblem of a dying and reviving branch. Many deriva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are given of the word <hi>phoenix</hi> which are omitted.</p>
            <p>Tis a Bird of <hi>Arabia</hi> (whereof there is never but one) living 660. years, (as <hi>Pliny</hi> relates) which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving the end thereof to be near at hand, builds her a Neſt in the top of a Palm tree, with hot ſpices Caſſia, Cinnamon, Myrrh, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:63183:60"/>which being ſet on fire by the ſun beams, her ſelf therein is therewith burnt, out of whoſe aſhes ariſeth a worm, which afterward groweth to be a <hi>phoenix:</hi> Many remarkable obſervations might hence be raiſed ſuitable to the preſent matter in hand. I ſhall onely touch upon a threefold parallel?</p>
            <p>Is not our King as another rare <hi>phaenix</hi> to us? May it not be ſaid of our Soveraign, as God by his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, <hi>Zach.</hi> 3.2. ſaid of <hi>Jehoſhna,</hi> who was wonderfully preſerved in the Captivity, yet Sathan ſtood at his right hand to reſiſt him, and ſought to afflict and trouble him: <hi>Is not this a brand taken out of the fire?</hi> The parallel holds very per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly, between our King and <hi>Jeho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhun,</hi> throughout the whole Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: Hath not his Majeſty been moſt miraculouſly preſerved from many Domeſtick and Foraign dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, by ſea and land, from plots of
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:63183:60"/>foes profeſt, and conſpiracies of falſe ſeeming friends, from publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que open perils of the ſword, and ſecret and private practiſes of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny wicked, cunning and cruell ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries: <hi>per mare, per terras, per ſara, perignes, per tot diſcrimina re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum:</hi> Through innumerable inef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fable difficulties, dangers, hath the Lord reſtored our King, from his exile to his Crown and dignity; and the Nations to Peace and ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as a brand taken out of the fire, kept from utter conſuming.</p>
            <p>To proceed with the parrallel, <hi>Jehoſhua</hi> was clothed with foule or filthy garments (as the text hath it) which the Lord Commanded to be taken from him, and cauſed him to be cloathed with change of ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and a faire Diadem to be ſet upon his head; And the Lord ſaid, I will bring forth the <hi>branch</hi> my ſervant; for loe the ſtone, that I have laid before <hi>Jehoſhua:</hi> upon
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:63183:61"/>one ſtone ſhall be ſeven eyes. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold I will cut out the graving thereof, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And in that day (that the Lord) ſhall ye call every man, his neighbour under the Vine and under the Fig tree, <hi>Zach.</hi> 3.5, 8, 9, 10. The application is evident, the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel applying it ſelf.</p>
            <p>How plainly and perfectly is this prophecy fullfilled by parallel in our Soveraign? are not thoſe foule blots and ſtains of falſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports and reproaches, calumnies, and ſcandalous aſperſions, by cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſlanderous detractors, now cleanſed and cleared, and his Majeſties untainted integrity co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered with the white rayment of unſpotted Innocence; clad with the garments of Glory and higheſt grandeur, and moſt richly arrayed, with the royall robes of moſt am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple &amp; illuſtrious renown, adorned with the faireſt Diadem of Royall
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:63183:61"/>Soveraignty and Dignity, and for a Crown to all his Majeſties Felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, crowned with the fur paſſing love, and faithfull loyalty, obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience and duty of his Subjects:</p>
            <p>And verſe the 8. <hi>I will bring forth the branch my ſervant;</hi> what branch more properly then grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from that royall root, of moſt ancient kingly Race; <hi>Plantaginet</hi> according to that of <hi>Ezekiel</hi> 34.29. by God promiſed to his people Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael. <hi>And I will raiſe up for them a plant of Renown, and they ſhall be no more conſumed, &amp;c.</hi> Hath not the Lord dealt as graciouſly with <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> as with Iſrael in this reſpect? Hath he not brought forth for <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> this bleſſed branch, this Royal Plant of Renown, <hi>Charlemaine Plantagenet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For lo the Stone ſaith the Lord) that I have laid before <hi>Jehoſhua;</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on one ſtone ſhall be ſeven eyes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="104" facs="tcp:63183:62"/>
            <p>To whom may this be more properly applied then to our <hi>Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemain,</hi> whom the Lord hath laid as a firm foundation, or chief cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſtone, whereon or by whom a ſure, certain and laſting form, and building of good and godly go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, both in Church and State, ſhall be ſettled, &amp; eſtabliſhed; And (to proceed with the parallel) upon this one ſtone ſhall be ſeven eyes, to whom more properly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicable then to that King at whoſe Nativity ſeven coeleſtial eyes vouchſafed a gracious aſpect, to ſignifie by that ſacred number of eyes, God would endue him with tranſcendent light of knowledge and wiſdome, that ſhould prepare and fit his Majeſty with rare and extraordinary gifts, for the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agement of thoſe great Affairs in point of Government; The num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber ſeven ſhewing a fulneſſe of light and knowledge, in ſo much
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:63183:62"/>that he ſhould not onely in ſtate Affairs have full prudence and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite policy in himſelf, but that others alſo ſhould admire his Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and ſeek knowledge, learn and take example from thoſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Rules, which he as a ſecond <hi>Solomon</hi> ſhould preſcribe, which doubt leſſe in all probability is moſt likely to be fallfilled in our Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign, whoſe excellency of matter and ſubſtance, together with the exquiſite Elegancy of Expreſſion, in all Letters, Declarations, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamations and other Writings, render his Majeſty the ſtile and Character (and that moſt deſerved<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) of a moſt pious, wiſe, and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Prince; moſt like to be the moſt potent Monarch that ever ſwayed the Scepters of theſe Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. And as the Lord promiſed to the ſaid Stone, with ſeven eyes to cut out the graving thereof, to take away the iniquity of the land
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:63183:63"/>in one day; And that in that day, ye ſhall call every man his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour under the Vine, and under the Fig-tree, <hi>verſe</hi> 9, 10. And how that ſhould be done, is ſhewed in the next Chap. <hi>Zach.</hi> 4.6. Neither by an Army, nor ſtrength, but by my ſpirit, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts. This day is this prophecy moſt perfectly fulfilled in our eyes. Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be our good God, who hath been ſo gracious both to his King and people; and let the glory be aſcribed onely to his Divine Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty.</p>
            <p>His Majeſty having been before proved to be as it were another <hi>Phaenix</hi> ſprung from that <hi>Phaenix</hi> Prince his Father, for Piety, Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and Patience, unparaleld, touching thoſe colours worn by the people, and called the Kings Colours, which being Crimſon, Purple, or a <hi>Phaenix</hi> colour, which bird builds her neſt in the top of a
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:63183:63"/>
               <hi>Palme</hi>-tree, ſome ſignifications in brief obſervations may be collect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
            <p>The purple being an embleme of wiſdome and councell <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>etimol: ex <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, quid ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fical <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> concilium cogito; quòd ſenatores &amp; Conſiliarij purpura ſunt induti, ſcat. ducit a bolla pro veſte ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natoria, ex <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, à conſilio,</hi> which importeth dignity and <hi>wiſdome,</hi> all things even the moſt inconſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, by providence conducing to the Elevation of the Kings honour even thoſe colours being argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of wiſdome, counſell and dignity belonging to the king.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Palme</hi>-tree alſo is an emblem of patience and victory to a perſon <hi>qui patientia vincit,</hi> who overcomes by patience. <hi>Quòd plana palma vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctoriam denotat: ſi ſupra palmae ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boris lignum magna onera imponas, non deorſum palma cedit, ſed adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus pondus reſurgit, &amp; quaſi vi reni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:63183:64"/>promenti. Palma ſignificat togant quid ſimulitudine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> palmae habet in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>textam palmata toga.</hi> The ſigne of Reward, Felieity, or Victory. His Maj. by his pious and prudent wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting &amp; patience hath overcome all difficulties &amp; dangers, recoverd his juſt rights, ſubdued his feirceſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries by a bloudleſſe conqueſt, brought to paſſe by divine provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and therefore moſt juſtly deſerves the palme, in ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne of, or reward for his happy Victory. See Revel. 7.9. <hi>Long White robes, ſigne of purity, palmes in their hands, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of victory and felicity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Much hath been ſaid touching the number ſeven, but not the moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of whatmay be ſaid thereof. The ſeven Starrs in the right hand of the ſonne of man, <hi>Revel.</hi> 1.16.20. <hi>Is there stiled there the mystery of the ſeven Stars,</hi> which is there de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared to be the Paſtors of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Churches which is ſet forth by
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:63183:64"/>the ſeven Golden Candleſticks, and by the right hand is ſignified divine protection. By the ſeven Starrs appearing at his Majeſties birth, what elſe can be ſignified but a ſeven Scepter, and that his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty ſhall be the paſtor, King, Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror of ſeven Kingdomes at leaſt, a plentifull benefactor to Paſtor and Church (which happily might be nominated, but at this time ſhall paſſe in ſilence) and that by divine affiſtance theſe Dominions ſhall be attained, before his Majeſties ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive at the age of ſeven times ſeven years, the major part 7 years ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and contained to his Majeſties poſterity, for ſeven generations or ſucceſſions enſuing: yea even un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till thoſe things which St. <hi>John. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel.</hi> 6. from the 12. to the end, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon opening the fixth ſeale of the book ſea. led with ſeven ſeals mentioneth to come to paſſe, ſhall be fullſilled.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mention was made before out of the propheſy of <hi>Zechariah,</hi> cap.
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:63183:65"/>3.9. of the ſtone which the Lord laid before <hi>Jehoſhua,</hi> and upon one ſtone there ſhould be ſeven eyes. The graving whereof, the Lord there promiſeth, himſelf to cut out, (that it might be perfect in all points, as a thing wrought by his own hand, as the marginall note hath it) and to take away the iniquity of the Land in one day, ſo that the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple might live in peace and quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, under their vines and fig trees as it followeth in the tenth verſ. of this chap. by way of parallel appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation is made to our <hi>Jehoſhua,</hi> our Soveraign <hi>Charlemaine;</hi> and doubt. leſſe moſt properly if we obſerve the ſcope of this, and the forth chapter next following; our King may be ſaid truly to be one ſtone with ſeven eye, a ſtone which God prepares with the ſeven gifts of his ſpirit mentioned <hi>Iſaiah.</hi> 11. from the firſt to the ſixt verſe, which is worth the reading and noting,</p>
            <pb n="111" facs="tcp:63183:65"/>
            <p>Again in <hi>Zachariah</hi> 4. what is meant by the Candleſtick all of Gold (which the Prophet ſaw) <hi>with a boul on the top of it and ſeven lampes; and ſeven pipes to the lamps: and two olive trees over it, one on the right ſide, and another on the left ſide of the boul.</hi> But the a royal Dukes, or the Graces of Gods good Spirit, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> he giveth increaſeth, &amp; continueth in thoſe perſons, whom he raiſeth to greatneſſe for his owne glory, and the good of his Church and people? And this is performed; <hi>non in Execitu nec in robore; ſed in ſpiritu meo dixit Deus exercituum.</hi> Though he be <hi>Dominus exercituum</hi> Lord of hoſtes; yet <hi>non exercitu,</hi> &amp;c. Neither by an Army, nor by ſtrength, but by his ſpirit ſhall <hi>Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rubabel</hi> build up his Church and people. <hi>Quis tu magne, mons co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram Zerubabel?</hi> Who art thou O Great Mountain before <hi>Zetubabel?</hi> Thou ſhalt be a plain, and he ſhall
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:63183:66"/>bring forth the head ſtone thereof with ſhouting, and crying, grace, grace unto it. The hands of <hi>Zerub. babel</hi> have laid the Foundation of his houſe; his hands ſhall alſo fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh it: <hi>&amp; ſcietis, quia dominus ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercituum m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſit me ad vos. Quis enint deſpexit dies parvos?</hi> Who hath deſpiſed the day of ſmall things? but they ſhall rejoice, and ſhall ſee <hi>Lapidem ſtanneum</hi> the ſtone of tinn in the hand of <hi>Zerubabel: Septem isti oculi, ſunt Domini, quid diſcur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant in univerſam terram</hi> thoſe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven are the eyes of the Lord which run through the whole world.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Zerubbabel</hi> is often mentioned in ſcripture for many worthy acts, he reedified the Temple in deſpite of all his Enemies <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a.</hi> 3.2. <hi>Zech</hi> 4 6.7.9, 10. He is called <hi>Sheſhbazzar.</hi> which ſignified joy in tribulation, <hi>Ezra.</hi> 1.8.15.14. and <hi>Berechrah Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemiah,</hi> 6.18. bleſſing or ſpeaking well of the Lord. The name <hi>Zerub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>babel,</hi>
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:63183:66"/>ſignifieth repugnant to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion; <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>enus à Confuſione</hi> ſtrang from Confuſion, or a diſperſion of confuſion, or a ſtranger at <hi>Babel.</hi> How directly ſuitable to our So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigns condition are theſe names of <hi>Jehoſhua,</hi> which ſignifies, Lord, Saviour, or the Lords Salvation; and <hi>Zerubbabel;</hi> and how properly applicable their offices and actions to his Majeſtie? Hath not the ſon of Man; the ſpiritual Saviour of the world, Chriſt Jeſus, in the mideſt of the ſeven golden Candleſtick, having in his right hand ſeven ſtars (the ſigne coeleſtial, ſhining in the preſence of the Sun at the birth of our King) been to the King a gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Saviour and Deliverer, but alſo made his Majeſty a true <hi>Joſhua,</hi> a ſaving Lord, a temporal Saviour, the Lords Salvation, for ſaving theſe three ſinking kingdomes? Is not his Majeſty by divine Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence become a zealous <hi>Zerub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>babel,</hi>
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:63183:67"/>a bright ſun, for diſperſing and diſpelling thoſe thick &amp; dark miſts and clouds of Confuſion, wherewith theſe diſtreſſed and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted Nations, have for a long ſeaſon been ſadly coverd &amp; almoſt conſumed. Hath not his Majeſty been repugnant to, and kept out as a ſtranger, whileſt this land was made a <hi>Babylon,</hi> a receptacle of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion? And is not his Majeſty in his return become, and may be truly termed a <hi>Shaſhbazzar,</hi> a joy in tribulation, and Olive bearer, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming with an Olive branch of peace to his people, and two Olive trees, the two Royall Dukes, his Majeſties brethre to ſettle their diſtractions? And howſoever thoſe that according to Gods word, and holy prophecies, may be world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings be contemned, and accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, as they are called in the 8. <hi>ver.</hi> of 3. of <hi>Zachariah, Viri portendentes,</hi> Monſtrous perſons, who preſage or apply any ſuch matter to his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty;
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:63183:67"/>yet, <hi>Ecce ſtella oritur ex Jacobo;</hi> And <hi>Ecee Adducam ſervum meum O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rientem,</hi> and <hi>Ecce vir Oriens Nomen enis. Zech.</hi> 3.9.16.12. The Coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtiall ſigne of ſeven Stars in the right hand of the ſun of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſhall ſhew himſelf and ſhine brightly. Our <hi>Jeheſhua,</hi> ſhall have a faire Diadem ſet upon his head, and be cloathed with glorious gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of gladneſſe, and his Crown flouriſh whileſt his enemies are cloathed with ſhame; And the hands of our <hi>Zerubabel,</hi> ſhall not onely lay the foundation of Gods houſe in his Church and State, but his Royall hands ſhall alſo finiſh it. The Great Mountain, (all his mightyeſt adverſaries) ſhall be a plain, be brought low? and ſhall know that the Lord hath called and ſent him to this purpoſe. For who ſhal deſpiſe the day of ſmal things, Let us not be diſcouraged, though beginnings ſeem ſmall &amp; deſpica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble yet we ſhall rejoyce; The ſtone
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:63183:68"/>which the <hi>Babylonian</hi> builders re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed, will be the head ſtone of the corner; and we ſhall ſee the Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous glitering ſtone of Tin <hi>Zech</hi> 4. 10 in the hand of our <hi>Zerubabel:</hi> The ſeven ſtars in the right hand of the Son of man; The ſeven eys of Lord which run through the world ſhall inlighten and enable his Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all heart with high &amp; heavenly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowments to go through with that great work which the Great <hi>Jehova</hi> hath ordeyned for him, and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined for his majeſty to accomp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh: And then to his Royal ſervant, our Soveraigne overcomming, will the Lord give to eat of the <hi>Manna</hi> that is hid (and not common to all and will give him a <hi>White ſtone</hi> (in ſigne of victory, honour and Gods favour) and in the ſtone a new name.</p>
            <p>This leadeth me to the next con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration or obſervation touching his Majeſties Name.</p>
            <pb n="117" facs="tcp:63183:68"/>
            <p>Having ſhewed ſomewhat touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his <hi>Majesties Nativity</hi> and the Coeleſtiall ſigne the Pleiades or ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Stars appearing thereat with the obſervations upon the <hi>Number ſeven;</hi> I ſhal (with all humility crave his Royall licence briefly to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs my mean meditations touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Majeſtyes Names; which may be ſaid to be three, <hi>Bonum nomen, bonum omen.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Naturall.</item>
               <item>2. Chriſtian.</item>
               <item>3. Politicall.</item>
            </list>
            <p>All proper to his Majeſty; Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, place, dignity, and promiſe, peace, honour, and happineſſe to his Majeſty; and the Kingdoms and people under his Dominions, and Government. <hi>Nomen quaſi notamen</hi> Name is a mark, note or ſigne by which any one perſon or thing is diſtinguiſhed from another: <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men quod notitiem facit, imago quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem qua quid noſcitur. Fest. nomen
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:63183:69"/>quaſi nonimen. Scal. lib.</hi> 76. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Vocabulum proprium quo rem ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellamus,</hi> a proper Denomination or terme, whereby we call a thing.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Vocabulum quod libet, quo ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid intelligibile, vel intellectum effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimus,</hi> any term or denomination, whereby we expreſſe any thing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligible or to be underſtood.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Id quod nomine expremitur: ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve perſona, ſuie res, etiam ipſa fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia, decus dignitas, famae exiſtimatio honor, Cultus, authoritas, jus poteſtas nomen per eo quod nominatur,</hi> &amp;c: Name is often uſed, for the perſon the thing, the family, the renown, dignity, fame, eſtimation, honour, worſhip, reverence, authority, right power and name; for the thing named.</p>
            <p>The name of the Lord is often taken for the Lord himſelf.</p>
            <p>When God moved the hearts of men to reſtore Religion after it
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:63183:69"/>had been long ſuppreſſed; Tis ſaid <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.26. <hi>Then began men to call up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Nam of the Lord.</hi> And <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> called on the Name of the Lord. <hi>Gen.</hi> 12.8.13.4. So did <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar. Gen.</hi> 16.13. and <hi>Izhak Gen.</hi> 26.25. <hi>Moſes</hi> did publiſh the name of the Lord. <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.3. The <hi>Levit.</hi> bleſſed Iſrael in the name of the Lord. <hi>Deut</hi> 10.8. Gods Name was in the Angel that guided <hi>Iſrael. Exod.</hi> 23.21. To put the name of God upon any, is to pray for him. <hi>Numb.</hi> 6.27. Who ſo blaſphemed Gods name, was ſtoned to death, <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vit.</hi> 24.11.14.16. What ſhall be done to thoſe who trace and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luminate the King, Gods vicege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent. <hi>David</hi> bleſſed the people in the name of the Lord. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.17, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Eliſha</hi> Curſed the children in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he name of the Lord, name is uſed for Power. <hi>Matt.</hi> 7.22. <hi>John</hi> 1.12. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd 22, 23. <hi>Acts</hi> 3.6. For Dignity <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.19. So Names are put for
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:63183:70"/>
               <hi>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n, Rev.</hi> 3.4. <hi>Acts</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.15. The Jews are commanded to deſtroy the <hi>name</hi> of <hi>Amalek</hi> from under hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, <hi>Deut.</hi> 25.19. The name of God is a ſtrong Tower, <hi>Prov.</hi> 16.10. <hi>David</hi> overcomes <hi>Goliah</hi> in the <hi>name</hi> of the Lord of Hoſts; 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17.45, 49. God exalteth the <hi>name</hi> of ſuch as keep his laws, <hi>Deut.</hi> 26.19. The Lord God made <hi>David</hi> to have a <hi>great name</hi> upon earth, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.9. And made <hi>Ioſhuah's name famous</hi> through all the world, <hi>Ioſh.</hi> 626. So will the Lord doe for our <hi>Ioſhua,</hi> our <hi>David.</hi> Make his name illuſtrious through the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe; and the Nations (over whom Gods makes his Majeſty Ruler) happy in and through hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> wiſe-and godly Government.</p>
            <p>Touching his Majeſty, <hi>tria no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> or <hi>nomen triplex;</hi> I ſhall no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> preſume to ſay much, onely hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly offer and tender thoſe conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, though imbecill and ſlen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:63183:70"/>touching the ſame, and begin with though the laſt, in time and order, yet not the leaſt in dignity and honour. The name Political King, in the Saxon tongue <hi>Cy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>g,</hi> in the German tongue <hi>Koning,</hi> the Dutch <hi>Kononingh, Koninck,</hi> a <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen,</hi> 1. <hi>ſcire,</hi> to know, <hi>Quod Rex ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra ſcientia imbutus eſſe debea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>;</hi> a King ought to be repleniſhed with true, ſound and ſaving knowledge; <hi>Cic.</hi> according to the Pſalmiſt: <hi>Et nunt reges intelligite, erudimini, qut indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catis terram.</hi> Pſal. 2.10. <hi>Ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a Kon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen,</hi> 1. <hi>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſe, polentemeſſe pollere.</hi> To be able, to be powerfull, to exce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, as far in rare parts, as in p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of place: <hi>Propter ſummam à Deo regi potestatem conceſſam;</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the large power given from God to Kings.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Latini poteſtates, vocant, principes potentes,</hi> The Latines call, powers potent princes: <hi>Konnen</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, i. <hi>valere, vnibus pollere.</hi> To be vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant,
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:63183:71"/>to excell in ſtrength, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>es<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vis, robur, potentia, id<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e à</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Koach,</hi> in the French tongue, King is called <hi>Roy,</hi> Italian <hi>Re,</hi> Spaniſh <hi>Rey,</hi> Latine <hi>Rex, à regendo,</hi> from ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling: In the Greek <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, i. <hi>fundamentum populi,</hi> the foundation, baſis, and eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his people; without whom no ſound, ſure, or firm building ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Church or State can be ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, eſtabliſhed: Hebrew, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lech,</hi> a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Malach (i. e.) regnavit imperavit.</hi> Thus much of the poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical name, but much more may be ſaid of the Office, power, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatives of Kings.</p>
            <p>This double Diſtichon ſeems not to be impertinent touching the power of Kings, upon theſe three words and things.</p>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <head>Rex, Lex, Grex:</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Lex ſine Rege, velut Lum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n, ſine So<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>uiſſet;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Rex ſine lege, v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>lut Sol ſine luce foret.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="123" facs="tcp:63183:71"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Grex Regem primo Legit, Rex cum Grege Legem,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Condidit, hinc legem Rex regit at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que Gregem.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>The powers, priviledges and prerogatives of Kings by Laws, II. ſages, and Cuſtomes, Divine and Humane, Rationall, Naturall, are many; The Perſon, preſence, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimony of Kings, by the Laws of our land, are in ſome ſort Sacred; The Villein of a Lord (which by law was ſeiſable) in the preſence of the King, could not be ſeiſed, for the preſence of the King, was a protection to him; which ſhews what reverence the law gives to the perſon of a King, <hi>plod Com.</hi> 322.27. <hi>Aſſi. pl.</hi> 49. Kings Courts are places priviledged from Arreſts; ſo ought the bodies of all his liege ſubjects in civill cauſes, as debt or the like, by the ancient law of the land to be freed from impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:63183:72"/>that they might ſerve his Majeſty and the Kingdomes, being members of that body, whereof his Majeſty in his politick capacity is the head; whereas by an unjuſt, chielf and wicked cuſtome, under colour of law, many thouſand mens bodies are maliciouſly upon bare pretences, buried alive in loathſome priſons, and reſtrained from the ſervice of their King and Country, to the great diſpleaſure o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> God, dammage of the King, by lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ng his ſubjects, diſhonour of the Nation, being branded with a mark of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> parrellel'd Cruelty, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal and opprobry, of the law in maintainting malice, revenge and oppreſſion; and deſtruction of many thouſand perſons and their Families. This is digreſſion, but it is hoped and prayed, that hereof his Majeſty will be gratiouſly plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to make a ſpeedy Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; which may prevent judgments upon the Nation.</p>
            <pb n="125" facs="tcp:63183:72"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Reges ſacro oleo uncti ſunt capacas ſpiritualis juriſdictionis,</hi> Kings are anointed with ſacred oyle; ſo was <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>David,</hi> by <hi>Samuel,</hi> Gods prophet by Gods appointment, and many others mentioned in the old Teſtament, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Their perſons are ſacred, as appears by that ſtrict Command given from God, by his prophet; <hi>Touch not mine anointed. Rex eſt perſona mixta cum ſacerdote, habet eccleſiaſtieam &amp; ſpirituale<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> juriſdictionem.</hi> All power and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority under the Divine Majeſty, whether it be Civil and Temporal, or Eccleſiaſtical and Spiritual Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction, belongs to the King, within all his Majeſties Dominions and is derived from the King; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the onely ſupream Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour over all perſons in all Cauſes, 33. <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. Ayde <hi>de Roy.</hi> 103 <hi>Fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rt.</hi> 10, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.7.16. 1. <hi>Ed.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>c.</hi> 1. <hi>Cawdries</hi> Caſe, <hi>Rep.</hi> 5. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Which Act is but Decta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ative of
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:63183:73"/>the Common Law. 1. <hi>Jacobi c.</hi> 1. <hi>vid.</hi> 9. <hi>Edw.</hi> 4. <hi>f.</hi> 1.</p>
            <p>The Lands of the King in law is called <hi>Patrimoniam Sacrum, Com. ſur. Littl. Sect.</hi> 4. What ſhal we think of thoſe that indeavour to bereave his Majeſty hereof, or withhold &amp; keep the ſame from the King? do they not commit Sacriledge? And is not Sacriledge a ſin, as much o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious to God, as offenſive to the King his Vicegerent? Sacriledge, whether of Gods or the Kings due, <hi>Qua Dei aut quae Domini Regis ſunt,</hi> of any thing that belongs to God or the King will prove a ſad lading which in the end, will ſink the beſt and ableſt bottome. A little of this Leaven may ſowre your whole lump; 'Twill be as <hi>Achans</hi> wedge, bring a curſe with it, a ſmall parcell of this ſacred patrimony, taken in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your Purchaſe, like the Kings waſte, may alter your Tenour in Gods bleſſings, and bring your
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:63183:73"/>whole fortune into Wardſhip. Thoſe that be pecants in this kind, let them not ever truſt to their ſmooth ſayling, ſudden ſhipwrack may ſelfe them in their ſeeming calmeſt ſecurity. It is a deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to a man to devoure that which is ſanctified, and after the Vows to inquire: If you believe <hi>Solomon,</hi> who had wiſdom from above, <hi>Pro.</hi> 10.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>As greater Power is by God, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to Kings and Emperours, and mighty Rulers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> greater parts, Diviner gifts alſo, of the minde, as Wiſdome, Prudence, Valour, and the like, are beſtowed on them: <hi>Saul</hi> being anointed King, is ſaid to have another heart given to him by God, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> 10.9. They have alſo nobler names, and greater and awfuller Reverence is due unto them, and many men are ſmitten with ſuch terrour of their Majeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call preſence, as though they were
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:63183:74"/>partakers of ſomewhat more the humanity, and that there were (as probable tis there are) ſome rayes of divinity evidently appearing and ſhining in their Perſons, Why elſe is God the great King of Kings pleaſed to be called King, and ſuffer his name to be communicated to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>m, and by a proper denomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion bath confirmed it to them. They are called mortall Gods, Her<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e's, Terreſtriall gods, compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ions of the Superior Gods, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> by whom the world is governed, and diſpoſed by their Laws, whom therefore at gods we receive, Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, Reverence, becauſe God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication of his name <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> them gods, I have ſaid, ye are all ſoms of the moſt high God; <hi>Pſal.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> And to <hi>Moſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> God ſaid I have made <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> elſe where he Gomman <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> concerning <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ye ſhall not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:63183:74"/>from the gods; And concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the reverencing and honcur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them, alſo deereeing riches and firſt fruits for them, and giving them power of the ſword, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidding any to curſe them, but en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyning obedience to be yeilded to them (though wicked) How much the rather then ought it to be rendred to good Kings.</p>
            <p>Antiquity called their Princes gods, &amp; worſhiped them, as divine powers, as <hi>Janus</hi> teſtifyeth in <hi>Ovid lib. d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> fast.</hi> 1.</p>
            <p>And divine <hi>Plato</hi> in his third book <hi>de Republica,</hi> appointed that Princes both alive &amp; dead, ſhould be celebrated with divine Honours which Inſtitutiton hath been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived amongſt the moſt and beſt Nations even from the firſt age, to deify their Princes with divine ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, a Gods vicegerent on earth and to conſecrate them with Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall memory. Hence they did
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:63183:75"/>impoſe their never dying names on little Provinces, Mountaines, Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, Lakes, Iſlands and Seas; and dedicated to them with great Pomp Pyramides, Coloſſes, triumphal ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, Trophes, Statues, Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, playes, feaſts; <hi>&amp;c,</hi> And alſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Heavens, Stars, Dayes and Months by their Name. Hence <hi>January</hi> from <hi>Janus, July</hi> from <hi>Juli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, August</hi> from <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> So <hi>Diet Mercurij</hi> from <hi>mercury Triſmegest. Dies Jovis</hi> from <hi>Jupiter,</hi> which cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome we read was obſerved, not onely by the Aegyptians, Greeks, and Romanes, but alſo by the then not ſo Civilized, (as now) a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, the Gothes, Danes, and Teu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours. Hence <hi>Saxo Grammaticus,</hi> being witneſſe, what day was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly called <hi>Dies Mercury,</hi> theſe call <hi>Othines</hi> day; and what day was formerly named from <hi>Jupiter,</hi> theſe do now call Thurſday, from <hi>Othin</hi> and <hi>Thor</hi> in times paſt Kings of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>
               <pb n="131" facs="tcp:63183:75"/>and <hi>Denmarke;</hi> neither are they for any other reaſon called <hi>Gothes,</hi> then that they call in their Language their Chiefeit God, <hi>Got.</hi> Hence alſo the Dutch are thus cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, becauſe they named the God <hi>Mars</hi> whom they worſhiped. <hi>Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan;</hi> By which name the <hi>Gaules</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo called <hi>Mercury.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Why may not the Moneth now called May, which ſome derive a made faction, from the moiſture then cauſed by the riſing of the Pleiades; be changed into <hi>Carol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> in regard of the Nativity of our <hi>Treſmegistus Carolus,</hi> in that month 1630. and the pleindes (whoſe riſing is in that moneth, called alſo <hi>Charls Waine</hi>) appeared at the time of his Birth on the 29th. day thereof on which day alſo his Majeſty returnd Triumphantly to London to his P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rliament in the year 1660. to the ineffectable ſurpaſſing Joy of his people. Surely heaven diſdain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:63183:76"/>no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o have a Coeleſtiall ſigne the Name of <hi>Charle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Why ſhould we not account it an Honour to the Nation to have this Moneth the beſt and chiefeſt in the year, dignifyed with the Name of that Perſon who is the onely Joy, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hrt and Honour of ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> horizon? His Birth Graced with a Coeleſtiall Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ribus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> His reſtitution the longing &amp; thirſting deſire of three Kingdoms; The ſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and ſtay of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Hotions, and reſtoring the col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lepſed Honour of our Countrey, a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>mber leſſe number with eyes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ard their Joy, tongues and lips <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> loud a cela<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ations expreſſing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of their hearts, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> hand<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dife up to h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aven <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ith prayers and praiſes. Though <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>uſe are not <hi>Minarula,</hi> yet they are <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> mirauda.</hi> very admirable.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> ſuch a people <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> view of their King, and ſuch a King in view of his People, hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:63183:76"/>their eyes to and fro, the one from the other, like the flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and falling of waters, a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciprocall and interchangeable mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of love between them. I know not what others think, but to me, it ſeemeth worthy to adde a Rubrick more to your Almanack, and make a new holy day amongſt you, and give it a new name, &amp; call it <hi>Charles</hi> day. The Pope maketh Jubilees at his pleaſure, why not this a Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilee, a yeare of extraordinary joy to theſe Nations? The like hath not happened for many generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: No not ſince <hi>Britain</hi> bate the name of a Nation, nor like to come to paſſe whileſt the world laſteth. And being a time and oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of ſo much Joy and happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to King and people, let their hearts unite in this one acceptable ſervice to heaven, to comfort them that Mourne in Sion, To ſpeak and act comfortably to and for many
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:63183:77"/>thouſands diſtreſſed and oppreſſed debtors, deſtructive members of Chriſt, who have for many years laine defolately and diſconſolately languiſhing, buried alive in Priſons ready to periſh, that they may ſay to the priſoners go forth, and to them that are in darkneſſe ſhew your ſelves, our Saviour diſdayned not to declare that the Lord had ſent him to preach good ridings to the poor, to binde up the broken hearted, to give liberty to the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, and to them that are bound, the opening of the priſon; to ſhew the acceptable yeare of the Lord, to comfort all that mourne. To Give unto them beauty for aſhes, that oile of joy for mourning, the garments of gladneſſe for the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of happineſſe; that ye might be called trees of righteouſneſſe, the planting of the Lord. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> neither can Kings appear like gods in any thing more, then in works of mercy.</p>
            <pb n="135" facs="tcp:63183:77"/>
            <p>But to return to ſpeak of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and powervouchſafed by God himſelf, to Princes. Kings if juſt and mercifull, are accounted Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions of the Gods, and indowed in ſome reſpects with the like pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. Hence they cure diſeaſes by their touch and word, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times command the times and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, as <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irgil</hi> ſung of <hi>Auguſtus.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>Nocte pluit tota, redeunt ſpectacula mane.</l>
                  <l>Diviſum imperium cum <hi>Jove Caeſar</hi> habet.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>It raines all night, in'th' morn the raies return;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Caeſar</hi> with <hi>Jove</hi> divided hath the Throne.</l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>And the Scripture teſtifyeth of <hi>Joſhuah,</hi> who fighting in <hi>Gibeon,</hi> commanded the Sun and Moon, ſaying, Sun ſtand ſtill in <hi>G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>beon,</hi> and thou Moon in the valley of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jalon,</hi>
               <pb n="136" facs="tcp:63183:78"/>and the Sun and Moon ſtood ſtill at his command, neither did the Sun ſet in the ſpace of one day, untill he had revenged himſelf of his enemies, and the Lord obeyed the voice of man; Alſo <hi>Moſes</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided the red Sea, and <hi>Joſhua, Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,</hi> and led the people over dry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhod; The like did <hi>Alexander</hi> the <hi>Macedonian,</hi> leading forth his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my;</p>
            <p>Sometimes princes are indowed with aprophetical ſpirit, as in many reſpects the ſweet ſinger of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> the Kingly Prophet <hi>David</hi> appears to be; moſt alike to whom not only in afflictions, but both in piety and prophecy. Was alſo our late pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetical King and kingly Prophet <hi>Carolu bonus primus, Charles le bon</hi> the good, the firſt, not onely <hi>regno, aut reguan do primus, ſed bonitate, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate prudent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a omnium predeceſſorum primus;</hi> whoſe propheticall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions in that incomparable di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:63183:78"/>piece, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, are many and many already evidently ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled: A particular Collection whereof in a peculiar ſmall vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumne by it ſelf, may hapily hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter be publiſhed. I ſhall herein men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion onely three or four at preſent.</p>
            <p>In his late Majeſties Meditation upon the Armies wilfull and wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſurpriſal of his Royal and Sacred perſon at <hi>Holmby,</hi> divers danger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous diviſions and diſtractions are by his Majeſtie predicted to enſue in the Houſes, the Army and City which accordingly came to paſſe, (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>) the Struglings of thoſe two twins (as his Majeſty then called the Preſbyterians and Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents) which lately one wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſed. And the breach ſtill not to grow wider, is as impoſſible, as lines drawn from the center, tis im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible not to divice from each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to much the wider, by how much they go further from the point of union.</p>
            <pb n="138" facs="tcp:63183:79"/>
            <p>That thoſe <hi>Babel</hi> Builders ſhould from diviſion fall to confuſion, and although they pretended the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> the deviding of their tongues and hands was but an ill <hi>Omen,</hi> and tended to fatall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.</p>
            <p>That Divine juſtice would bring it ſo to paſſe, that they which by Tumults firſt occaſion'd the raiſing of armes, muſt be chaſtened by their own army for new Tum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lts.</p>
            <p>The plea againſt tumults holds good, which before was condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, whilſt they are Judges of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, they are forced to condemn themſelves.</p>
            <p>And hereupon ſaith his Majeſty prophetically, I ſee vengeance ſhall perſue and overtake (as the mice and rats are ſaid to have done a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop in <hi>Germany</hi>) them that thought to eſcape and fortifie themſelues moſt impregnably againſt it, both by their multitude and compliance;
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:63183:79"/>and whom the Laws cannot, God will puniſh by their own crimes and hands. His Majeſty with a pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous pity proceeds, and towards the Parliament, City and all his people which were miſerably miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and miſtaken, ſaith this good King, I was ſorry to ſee them do, or ſuffer unworthily, I never had ſo ill thought of them as to diſpaire of their Loyalty to me; which mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtakes might ecclips, but I never be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved malice had quite put out. I looked on them as Chriſt did ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time over <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> as objects of my prayers and tears, with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſionate grief, foreſeeing thoſe ſeverer ſcatterings which will cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly befall ſuch as wantonly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to be gathered to their duty; (marke well this propheticall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion) fatal blindneſſe frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly attending &amp; puniſhing will full; ſo that men ſhall not be able at laſt to prevent their ſorow who would
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:63183:80"/>not timely repent of their ſins, nor ſhall they be ſuffered to enjoy the comforts, who ſecurely neglect the counſells belonging to their peace, They will finde that Brethren in Iniquity, are not far from becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing inſolent enemies, there being nothing harder then to keep ill men ſtill in our minde. Vulgar compliance with any illegall and extravagant waies, like violent mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in Nature, ſoon grow's wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of it ſelf, and ends in a refracto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſullenneſſe; peoples rebounds are often in their faces, who firſt put them upon thoſe violent ſtrokes.</p>
            <p>Let the accurſed Authors and abetters of that Prodigious horrid Rebellion, deny if they dare or truely can, his late moſt Religious Majeſty to be a true Prophet, whoſe predictions are in many reſpects ſo p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rfectly fulfilled upon them their Families and adherents, and daily
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:63183:80"/>ſhall we finde a more full perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance in future to be accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
            <p>In theſe divine Meditations, of his late Majeſty, touching Death, after the Votes of non-Addreſſes, and his Majeſties cloſe impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in <hi>Carisbrook</hi> Caſtle; theſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nſuing expreſſions, who can deny <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o be prophetique. <hi>There are I know but few ſteps, between the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and the Graves of Princes.</hi> And after; <hi>I doubt not but mine Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ency will finde him both my Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor and my Advocate who is my one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y judge, and whom I own as King of Kings. Nor will the ſuffer thoſe men long to proſper in their</hi> Babell, <hi>who build it with the boughs, and cement it with the blood of their Kings, My blood will cry aloud to heaven for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>engeance, but I beſeech God not to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oure his wrath upon the generality of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he people, who have either deſcerted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, or engaged againſt me, through the
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:63183:81"/>Artifice and Hypocriſie of their lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, whoſe inward horrour will be their Tormentor; nor will they after eſcape exemplary judgments. I am confident they will finde Avengers of my death among themſelves: The in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries I have ſuſtained from them ſhal be first puniſhed by them, who agreed in nothing ſo much, as in oppoſing me. Their impatience to bear the loud cry of my bloud; ſhall make them think no way better to expiate it, then by ſhed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding theirs, who with, them, moſt thirsted after mine. The ſad confuſions following my deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, are already preſaged &amp; confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to me by thoſe, I have lived to ſee, ſince my troubles; and God alone (who onely could) hath many wayes pleaded my cauſe; not ſuffering them to go unpuniſhed, whoſe confederacy in ſinne is their onely ſecurity; who have cauſe to fear, that God will both further divide, and by mutuall vengeance afterward deſtroy them.</hi>
               <pb n="143" facs="tcp:63183:81"/>And again afterwards by a lively Faith his Princely reſolution con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, <hi>I Conquerer ſhall be more then through Chriſt, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And in the cauſe ſo long diſputed by the ſword, between me and my cauſeleſſe adverſaries, I doubt not but his righteous Judgement will confute their fallacies, who from worldly ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, rather like Sophiſters then good christians) draw thoſe popular con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſions, for Gods approbation of their accounts, whoſe wiſe providence (we know) oſt permits many events, which his revealed word (the onely clear; ſafe, and fixed rule of good a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions and good conſcien<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cs) in no ſort approves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The application of theſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſies are plaine and facile to the meaneſt apprehenſions.</p>
            <p>Hath not divine prudence, made all the ſeditions <hi>Shebaes, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ebell ous, Corake,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Simeons</hi> and <hi>Lepi's</hi> bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren in iniquity, even all the Kings
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:63183:82"/>enemies by diviſion, among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, like to the mad <hi>Midiannes</hi> inſtruments of ruine and diſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, one to another, of revenging the injuries done to his Majeſty &amp; ſo clearing his innocency, and the juſtice of his cauſe?</p>
            <p>Let it be conſidered, and obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved what is become of all or the moſt part of that pernitious party of the Long Black Parliament and their Army, which ſo vehemently proſecuted and perſecuted his late Majeſty and his friends and poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and it cannot but be confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and without contradiction con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded. That as God is juſt in all his juſt judgments and righteous in all his, waies, ſo his maje<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ries predicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons have not failed, but received a ſad and evident accompliſhment, to the confuſion of the faces of his adverſaries vindication of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Honour, and Gods glory.</p>
            <p>Among the reſt, <hi>in perpetuam
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:63183:82"/>rei memoriam,</hi> that O. P. <hi>omen pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditionis, onus &amp; odium prineipis &amp; patria,</hi> ought be recorded, <hi>&amp; atro carbone notandum,</hi> to all poſterity, O. P. (for pretended writing of which two Letters with the words <hi>Occidiſti Poſſedisti;</hi> under (rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to the ſaying of <hi>Eliah</hi> to <hi>Ahab</hi>) 1 <hi>King.</hi> 21.19. the Author of this Tract, indured long and hard impriſonment) which O.P. proved to be not a Protector, a title un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthily aſſumed, but rather a Projector, <hi>perditionis &amp; proditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis non ſolûm principi &amp; patriae, ſed fataliter &amp; finaliter posteritatiſuae;</hi> which (as a true token of divine Judgment) were ruined in an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, by their own neer relations, which by <hi>O. P.</hi> were raiſed to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve them.</p>
            <p>His late Majeſty in a Letter of Adviſe to the then Prince of <hi>Wales,</hi> our now moſt bleſſed King, hath in many reſpects manifeſted himſelf
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:63183:83"/>to be a moſt wiſe, and prudent Prince, by his political inſtructions in State Affaires; a moſt pious Prieſt and Eccleſiaſtes in his divine Doctrines and directions, and a true Prophet, in his infallible pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions, the particulars whereof, as it would require much time to recite, expreſſe and apply, ſo, (I doubt) it would be accounted more tedious, then requiſitely ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to repeat the ſame, being al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſet down moſt fully and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent for obſervation in that un; parrallel'd piece <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>I ſhall onely mention briefly from his late Majeſty <hi>Charls le ſag</hi> and <hi>le bon,</hi> the mirrour of piety, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience and prudence, ſome few pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts or preſcriptions of adviſe to prayers for, and prophecies touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his now moſt hopefull and happy Majeſty.</p>
            <p>Touching Afflictions, Religion
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:63183:83"/>and Reſolution in all conditions; a Crown upon ſordid diſhonourable irreligious terms is not worth ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king up, or enjoying: <hi>Keep you to true principles of piety, virtue and bonour, you ſhall never want a king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus by our late Majeſty of bleſſed memory, to our now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned King was it written, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning, trouble and affliction, whereby to gain wiſdom in youth.</p>
            <p>This advantage of wiſdome, you have above moſt princes: That you have begun, and now ſpent ſome years of diſcretion, in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of troubles and exerciſe of patience, wherein piety and all vertues both morall and politicall, are commonly better planted to a thriving, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rees ſet in Winter, then in warmth and ſerenity of times; or amidſt thoſe delights, which uſually attend princes Courts in times of peace and plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:63183:84"/>which are prone either to root up all plants of true vertue and honour; or to be contented onely with ſome Leaves and withering formalities of them, without any reall fruits, ſuch as tend to the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like good; for which Princesſhould alwayes remember they are born, and by providence deſigned.</p>
            <p>The evidence of which diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Education, holy Writ affords us in the Contemplation of <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Rehoboam:</hi> The one prepared by many afflictions for a flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing kingdome; The other ſoftned by the unparalleld proſperity of <hi>Solomons</hi> Court; and ſo corrupted to the great dimunution, both for Peace, Honour, and Kingdome, by thoſe flatteries, which are as unſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable from proſperous Princes, as flies are from fruit in ſummer, whom adverſity like cold weather drives away.</p>
            <p>I had rather you ſhould be
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:63183:84"/>
               <hi>Charts le bon,</hi> then <hi>le grand,</hi> good then great; I hope, God hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned you to be both; having ſo early put you into that exerciſe of his gifts and graces, beſtowed upon you, which may beſt weed out all vitious inclinations, and diſpoſe you to thoſe princely endowments and imployments, which will moſt gain the love, and intend the wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare of thoſe over whom God ſhall place you.</p>
            <p>Who ſeeth not this divine dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction digeſted, pious prayer heard and granted, and the propheſie of good and great fulfilled? What greater, what better Prince in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome, in Europe, then our moſt illuſtrious renowned <hi>Charlemain?</hi> and unto this goodneſs and great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe attaining, not mollifie and effeminated with the wanton plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of a proſperous Court; but <hi>per mare, per terras, per tot diſcrimina rearum;</hi> with <hi>David,</hi> tryed and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:63183:85"/>tyred with terrours and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles; yet clearly prepared to be at laſt, <hi>terque quaterque beatus,</hi> by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine providence reſtored to a tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple Crown, his juſt right and due by Nature, and legal deſcent, and deſigned to <hi>ſeptem, plici ſceptro,</hi> a ſevenfold ſcepter, which the <hi>Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentrional Lion,</hi> ſhall obtain and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy before, <hi>ter ſepties,</hi> or <hi>ſepties tres,</hi> Number of years, and the major part of this ſevenfold ſcep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, ſhall be gained into the power &amp; Dominion of this Septentrional Lyon, before three and ſeven years expire: the extent of whoſe time of years or age ſhall be to ſeventy three. And by the age of 37. that ſtar of <hi>Sybilla</hi> in the North, ſaid to enlighten the world, ſhall ſhine moſt gloriouſly on this Septentrio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Lyon, whoſe fame ſhall ring, and the terrour of whom ſhall be reſounded through't the Univerſe; This digreſſion I cannot avoid, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:63183:85"/>drawn thereunto by that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine ſpirit, from whoſe dictates I am directed to declare, what by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine deſignment is determined touching this tranſcendent ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>excellent perſon; but to return to the conſideration of his late Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties propheticall expreſſions. Hath not Almighty God moſt graciouſly directed all thoſe black lines of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, which he was pleaſed to draw on his late Majeſty, &amp; alſo on his Majeſty that now is (who hath drank liberally alſo of that cup of carefull troubles) unto a centre of true happineſſe? even to draw them nearer to himſelf; their ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows are become Gods Phyſick; having that in healthfulneſs, which was wanting in pleaſure: The Fathers ſufferings ſhall be doubly recompenced in ſolaces to the Sons.</p>
            <p>Is not that ſly old Serpent, which pretended new lights at
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:63183:86"/>length by his deeds of darkneſs, detected to be a proſelyte to the Father of Lyes, by whoſe perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and inſtigation, he an his adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents proſecuted ſo violently the Innocents? And that ſeeming Saint which aſſumed the ſhape of an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel of Reformation, diſcovered to be the Devill of Rebellion? Have we not ſeen the Serpent devoure the Dove. Hath not the faith of ſome proved meer Faction, and their Religion Rebellion? Have they not alwayes made their Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, Gods? And under the colours of Piety, have not there marcht their ambitious policies, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with greateſt ſecurity, but ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe, as to the populacy? Hath not <hi>Jacob</hi> voice been heard, when <hi>Eſaus</hi> hands have been felt? Hath not God made his Majeſty an happy Inſtrument of diſſipating theſe deviliſh Factions, which would have deſtroyed the Nations? Hath
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:63183:86"/>not a divine hand divided them to ſo high a rivalry as ſets them more at de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiance againſt each other, then againſt their firſt Antagoniſt? as his Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſty predicted. Have not thoſe rough horns of private mens covetous and ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous deſignes, made a clear diſcovery of themſelves, which were at firſt wrapt up and hidden under the ſoft and ſmoth pretenſions of Religion, Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation and liberty? And as the woolf is not leſſe cruel, ſo will he be more juſtly hated, when he ſhall appear no better than a woolf in ſheeps cloathing. The mountains of congealed factions, by the ſunſhine of Gods mercy, and the ſplendor of our Soveraigns vertues are thawed and diſſipated; and the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed vulgar hath learned; that none are greater oppreſſors of their Eſtates, Liberties and Conſciences, then thoſe men that entitle themſelves the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons and Vindicators of them, onely to Uſurp power over them; Doe not theſe deceiptions daily vaniſh, and the vazards fall off a pace? The mask of Religion in the face of Rebellion, will no longer ſerve to hide ſome mens de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtable deformities in their damnable deſignes.</p>
            <pb n="154" facs="tcp:63183:87"/>
            <p>The precepts, prayers and prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies of his late Majeſty to, for, &amp; touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our now king &amp; his kingdoms, are very remarkable and well worthy ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation; ſome whereof I have before mentioned, and ſome few hereafter I ſhall ſpecifie: As firſt advice and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept touching Religion; I doe require and entreat you as your Father and your King, that you would never ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer your heart to entertain or receive the leaſt check againſt or diſaffection from the true Religion eſtabliſhed in the Church of <hi>England.</hi> I tell you, I have tryed it and after much ſearch, and many diſputes have concluded it to be the beſt in the world, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> many incitements to the imbracing and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing thereof; which holy directions his now Majeſty hath as dutifully and faithfully obſerved, what then is or ought to become of thoſe curſed ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumniators, under whoſe lips is the poiſon of Aſpes, which charged the late and this religious Kings with popery (which however contemptible here, yet teaching no ſuch principles, as have been held and practiſed by ſome of thoſe who would be accounted the
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:63183:87"/>modern principall pillars of piety and Religion in theſe Nations)</p>
            <p>Another direction touching revenge, ſavouring of a ſoul truly divine, <hi>notatu dignum; Let no paſsion betray you to any ſtudy of revenge upon thoſe whoſe own ſin and folly will ſufficiently puniſh them in time. As your quality ſets you beyond any Duel with any ſubject; ſo the nobleneſſe of your minde muſt raiſe you above the meditating any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, or executing your anger upon the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, you will finde more inward complacency in pardoning one, than in puniſhing a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand</hi> Many other Obſervations, and thoſe material, touching his Majeſties Name, Natural and Chriſtian, his roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Brethren, the two Renowned Dukes of <hi>York</hi> &amp; <hi>Gloceſter,</hi> and other remarka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble matter, relating to the noble Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral <hi>Monke,</hi> not unworthy conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, are penned and were intended at this time to be publiſhed, but are reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved for a particular Treatiſe-hereafter; And this Tract at preſent concluded, with y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> prophetical prayer, or praying prophecy of the late moſt pious King, Prieſt, &amp; Prophet, of moſt bleſſed memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for &amp; touching his now Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſty (then Prince) in a good part granted, and in
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:63183:88"/>a faire forwardneſs like to be fulfilled. <hi>That Almighty God will make his Majeſty, an Ankor or Harbor rather, to theſe toſsed wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therbeaten Kingdomes</hi> (as is already ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed) his Majeſty being become an happy haven of reſt and ſafety after ſo great danger of the Kingdomes <hi>nau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fragie.</hi> And by his wiſdome, juſtice, piety and fortitude a repairer of what the folly, wickedneſſe, ambition and Avarice of ſome men have ſo ruined; as to leave nothing in Church or ſtate; to the Crown, the Nobility, the Clergy, or the Commons, either as to laws, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties or eſtates, order, honor, conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, or lives. This is in a hopefull way by his Maj. through his Parl. preparing and by a proſperous progreſſe therein, like to attain ſpeedy and happy perfection. Happy times I hope will attend his Maj. wherein as all good ſubjects will be ſatisfied with the bleſſings of his preſence and virtues; ſo will they by preceding ſad experiences have learned, <hi>That religion to their God, and loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty to their King cannot be parted, without both their ſin and their infelicity;</hi> as God promiſed, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 132.17, 18. The Kingly prophets prayer ſhall put a period to this preſent diſcourſe, wherein he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired God to purge his Church from Hypocrites and Rebels. <hi>Do well, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Lord, to thoſe that be good and true in their hearts: but thoſe that turn aſide, by their crooked wayes, them ſhall the Lord lead with the workers of iniquity, but peace ſhall be up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Iſrael.</hi> Pſ. 125 4, 5.</p>
            <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:63183:88"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
